<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vvell of wisedome, conteining chiefe and chosen sayinges vvhiche may leade all men to perfect and true vvisedome, as vvell to Godvvard as to the vvorlde Gathered out of the five bookes of the olde testament, especially belonging to vvisedome, that is to say, the prouerbes of Salomon, Ecclesiastes, Canticum, Sapientia and Ecclesiasticus, and bestowed in usuall common places in order of A. B. C. By T. C.</title>
            <title>Bible. O.T. Selections.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1577</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 66 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19071</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111199</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846598</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846598</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11578</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19071)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11578)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 203:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vvell of wisedome, conteining chiefe and chosen sayinges vvhiche may leade all men to perfect and true vvisedome, as vvell to Godvvard as to the vvorlde Gathered out of the five bookes of the olde testament, especially belonging to vvisedome, that is to say, the prouerbes of Salomon, Ecclesiastes, Canticum, Sapientia and Ecclesiasticus, and bestowed in usuall common places in order of A. B. C. By T. C.</title>
                  <title>Bible. O.T. Selections.</title>
                  <author>Cogan, Thomas, 1545?-1607.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 106, [7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Vautroullier for VVilliam Norton,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1577.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T. C. = Thomas Cogan, who signed the dedication.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Selections --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11578:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11578:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:11578:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11578:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VVELL OF WISEDOME, CONTEI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NING CHIEFE AND CHOSEN ſayinges vvhich may leade all men to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect and true vviſedome, as vvell to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard as to the vvorlde: <hi>GATHERED OVT OF THE FIVE bookes of the olde Teſtament, eſpecially belonging to VViſedome, that is to ſay, the Prouerbes of Salomon, Eccleſiaſtes, Canticum, Sapientia and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, and beſtowed in vſuall common pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in order of A. B. C. By T. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROVERBES 2.</bibl> It is the Lorde that geueth wiſedome, out of his mouth commeth knowledge and vnderſtanding.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Vautrollier, featuring an anchor surrounded by laurels (McKerrow 164)</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q>ANCHORA SPEI</q>
               </head>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Thomas Vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>troullier for VVilliam Norton.</hi> 1577.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11578:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11578:3"/>
            <head>TO THE WORSHIPFVL M. NEVVELL SOTHERTON, CLERKE OF THEXTRETES OF the Queenes Maieſties Court of Exchequer: grace, mercy and peace from God the Father, and from the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all the giftes that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer God beſtovved on ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, vviſedom excelleth: vvhich is not only by King Salomon and his vvritinges ſincerely vvitneſſed, but alſo by good gouernment &amp; orders of diuers Princes, rulers, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers, and ſtates of common vvelths, from time to time in euery age confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. And although the bookes of the olde Teſtament named Sapientiall, ſet forth directly neither lavv, propheſie nor hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie, yet doe they plainly expreſſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of vviſedom, and arguments inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent thereunto. And vvhen as for my ovvne inſtruction I had of late collected
<pb facs="tcp:11578:4"/> the chiefeſt ſayings to the order of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon places, I did conſider that they pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished might ſomevvhat profit others, being applied to proper intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. And thereupon vnderſtanding of your ſpeciall zeale to good learning, and ſingular imitation of the fruites contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſaid bookes, haue thought good to preſent theſe my labours vnto you as a patrone conuenient for ſuch a vvorke. For myne ovvne parte I acknovvledge that by reading the bookes aforeſayd, I haue obtained more vnderſtanding euen in vvorldly affayres, then my yong yeres by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce haue taught me, or my tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels at Oxford in the ſtudy of profane au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors directed me. And no maruell, for vvho in vviſedom either is or hath ben at any tyme like vnto Salomon, is it not vvritten in the third of Kings &amp; third chapter, that vpon prayer made by Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon for an vnderſtanding heart, God ſayd vnto him, becauſe thou hast asked this thing, and hast not asked long life, neither riches, nor the liues of thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies:
<pb facs="tcp:11578:4"/> See I haue done according to thy petition, and beholde I haue geuen thee a vviſe and an vnderſtanding heart, ſo that there vvas none like thee before thee, neither after thee shall any ariſe like vnto thee. And againe in the tenth chapter of the ſame booke: that the Queene of Saba came to Ieruſalem from the vttermoſt coaſtes of the land to heare and ſee the vviſedom of Salomon, and in ſumme that king Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exceded all the Kings of the earth in riches and vviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that all the vvorld reſorted to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon to heare his vviſedome vvhich God had put in his heart. This being true of vvhom then may vve better learne vviſedom then of the vviſest? VVhoſe ſayinges becauſe they be alſo of the holy ſcripture, ought vvith more heede to be marked, and vvill doubtles in euery good mans heart be the deeper imprinted. For the ſayinges of the vviſe and vnvviſe are not vvith vviſe men of like autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, neither are the ſayinges of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſcriptures and of other vvriters
<pb facs="tcp:11578:5"/> likevviſe to be valued. But other mens ſayings ſo farre allovved as by ſcripture they may be confirmed. Then although Thales, Solon, Chilo, Pitachus, Bias, Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus, Periander, vvhich vvere named the ſeuen vviſe men of Grecia: If Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras, Socrates, Plato, Ariſtotle, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtus and many moe, both vviſe and learned Philoſophers haue vttered ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ſayinges and ſentences inducing to vertue and vviſedom. Yet are not their ſayings likevviſe to be regarded as the ſayings of Salomon or Ieſus Syrach, nay in reſpect of Salomon they vvere all but fooles: neither vvas their vviſedom true and perfect vviſedom, becauſe they vvanted the feare &amp; right knovvledge of God. VVherefore ſuch learned men as haue tranſlated their ſayinges into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, and ſet them forth togither vvith the ſayings of Salomon, and other out of the holy ſcripture, as they are to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for their diligence, vvilling to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit others that can not vnderstande the Latine tongue, ſo are they not to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:11578:5"/> for mingling <hi>Sacra prophanis,</hi> vvhether it be touching doctrine, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation. Notvvithstanding I graunt many of their ſayings to be good, and to leade a man to vviſedom, neyther doth the one take avvay the other, but ought as they be in deed ſo to be eſtemed. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, although it vvell appeare that all theſe ſayings are and haue bene knovvne to you longe ſince, for that you haue traueled for triall of doctrine, and quieting of your conſcience thorough out the holy Byble ſufficiently, yet may theſe common places, (vvhich is the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of abridgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts) bring you in mind of many thinges red before. But they are not gathered for your better inſtruction or others, vvhich be vviſe and learned, and able of them ſelues to gather much better &amp; in better order, but for the rude and ignorant, vvho though they can read, yet haue not iudgement to diſcerne and to diſſeuer ſentences. And as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the name geuen to the booke, it is taken out of the eighteene chapter of the
<pb facs="tcp:11578:6"/> Prouerbes, vvhere I reade it vſed in like ſenſe, <hi>videlicet,</hi> the vvords of the vviſe mans mouth are like a full ſtreame. And againe in the firſt of Eccleſiaſticus, Gods vvorde in the height is the vvell of vviſedom. God graunt therefore that out of this vvell vve may dravv plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly both true vviſedome to guide vs in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and true doctrine to direct vs in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuing, that in the end vve may fully taſt of him vvhich geueth all true vviſdom, vvhich is the very fountaine of life Chriſt Ieſus, and here moſt hartely I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to accept this dedication in good part as a perfect ſignification of beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence in him that vvisheth you increaſe of felicitie, and all vertuous actions thorough the benefite and rule of vviſedom. From Oriall college in Oxford, the xx. of Auguſt. anno 1573.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to commaund, THOMAS COGAN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11578:6"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> might ſeeme (gentle rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) to haue attempted a needeles work in ſetting forth ſentences of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which (God be tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked) through daily reading and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching are nowe rife in euery mans mouth: but the cauſes mouing me thereto, are before alleaged in mine epiſtle. And in deede I haue ſet forth nothing but Scripture: gathering the places as the chapters and bookes are placed in the Bible: and in the ſame tranſlation which is commonly vſed and by authoritie approued. Which places being well conſidered, may geue vs to vnderſtand, that God of his goodnes, hath layd before vs through his diuine wiſedom, not only our du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie towarde him, and right beleefe in him: but alſo in ſome part or other of the ſcripture, how we ought to deale
<pb facs="tcp:11578:7"/> in worldely affayres, yea more then that, what dyet we ought to keepe in eating &amp; drinking, yea what maners we ought to vſe both at the table and els where. So that the Bible may ſeme to containe all thinges neceſſary to be knowen of vs any maner of way. But may we not learne wiſedome other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where then in the ſcripture? yes tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, yet ſo as S. Auguſt. writeth <hi>de doct. Chriſt. cap. vlt. Quicquid homo extra di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicerit, ſi noxium eſt, hic damnatur: ſi v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile eſt, hic inuenitur: &amp; quum ibi quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que inuenerit omnia, quae vtiliter alibi didicit, multo abundantius ibi inueniet ea, quae nuſquam aliter inuenire potuit.</hi> And certes, in the reading of Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and Ieſus Syrach, I founde di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſayinges, which be alſo red in prophane writers, as in the Prou. 22.<note place="margin">Prou. 22.</note> Teach a childe in his youth what way he ſhould goe, &amp;c. The like is in the Poet Horace. <hi>Quo ſemel eſt imbuta re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens ſeruabit odorem teſta diu.</hi> In Eccle. What manner of man the ruler of the<note place="margin">Eccle. 10.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:11578:7"/> citie is, ſuch are they that dwel there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo. The ſame is alleaged by Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro out of Plato. <hi>Quales in republica principes, tales reliqui ſolent eſſe ciues.</hi> And in Eccle. 12. In heauines &amp; trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a man ſhall know his friende. The ſame is vſed of Cicero in Lelio. <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus certus in re incerta cernitur.</hi> Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe may be ſayde of a greate number moe. Whereby are vnderſtande that the ſame God which gaue wiſedome abundantly vnto Salomon, hath like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe powred ſome ſparkes of wiſdom into heathen mens hearts, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to if they had ioyned true knowledge of God, then had they bene wiſe men in deede. Yet are not they ſo greatly to be blamed as thoſe Chriſtians, at leaſt wiſe by name, (though in deede much worſe then heathen or Infidels) which reading and hearing the true wiſedome of God, doe vtter in doing moſt deuiliſh policie. Nay many eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh<note place="margin">Anglus Italiatus.</note> men being Italianate, doe proue the prouerbe true to be deuils incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,
<pb facs="tcp:11578:8"/> hauing more delite in the prince of darkenes, ſet forth by Machiauell,<note place="margin">Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel.</note> or his diſcourſe leading headlong to hell, then in Gods word, which is the well of wiſedome, or the euerlaſting co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, which are the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance vnto it. So that a man may ſee great difference in wiſedome, which alſo is noted in Eccleſiaſticus 19. after<note place="margin">Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticus 19.</note> this maner: The feare of God is all vviſedome, and he that is a rightwiſe man keepeth the law. As for the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of wickedneſſe, it is no wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: and the prudence of ſinners is no good vnderſtanding: it is but wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, and abomination, &amp; blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of wiſedom, which alſo is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the heathen Philoſopher Plato: <hi>Scientia quae eſt remota à iuſticia, callidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas potius quam ſapientia eſt appellanda.</hi> Yet nowe a dayes, vice beareth the name of vertue. Subtiltie I ſay, hath the countenance of wiſedom, yea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe which (as men ſay) be no ſmall fooles. But God in the ende, as
<pb facs="tcp:11578:8"/> S. Paule witneſſeth, Corin. 1. will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy<note place="margin">Corin. 1.</note> the wiſedom of the wiſe, and wil caſt away the vnderſtanding of the prudent. For the fooliſhnes of God is wiſer then men: and the weakeneſſe of God is ſtronger then men. God graunt that the wiſe of the world, may in the ende be as the fooliſh whom God hath choſen. Yea as Socrates &amp; Plato with ſome other of the beſt and wiſeſt Philoſophers, whom notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their miſ beleefe, God of his infinite mercy hath recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to grace, as Iuſtine the Martyr, S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue iudged.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:11578:9"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>IAMES 1.</bibl>
               <p>IF any of you lacke wiſedom, let him aſke of God which geueth to all men indifferently, and caſteth no man in the teeth: and it ſhall be geuen him.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>VVIS. 9.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>The prayer of Salomon to obtayne wiſedom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O God of my fathers, and Lord of mercies, thou that haſt made all thinges with thy word, and ordayned man thorough thy wiſedom, that he ſhoulde haue dominion ouer the creatures which thou haſt made: that he ſhould order the world ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to equitie and righteouſnes, and execute iudgement with a true heart: geue me wiſedome which is euer about thy ſeate, and put me not out from among thy children: for I thy ſeruaunt and ſonne of thy handmaiden, am a feeble perſon, of a ſhort time, and too yong to the vnderſtanding of iudgement &amp; the lawes. And though a man be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo perfect among the children of men, yet if thy wiſedome be not with him, he ſhall be nothing regarded. O ſend her out of thy holy heauens, and from the throne of thy Maieſtie, that ſhe may be with me and labour with me: that I may knowe what is acceptable in thy ſight, for ſhe knoweth &amp; vnderſtandeth all thinges: and ſhe ſhall leade me ſoberly in my workes, and preſerue me in her pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſo ſhall my workes be acceptable.</p>
            </q>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="subject">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:11578:9"/>
            <head>ADVERSITIE AND proſperitie.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 7. 16.</note> VSe well the time of proſperitie, and remember the time of misfortune: for God maketh the one by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo that a man can finde nothing elſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 2. 4. 5.</note> Whatſoeuer hapneth vnto thee, receaue it: ſuffer in heauines and be patient in thy trouble. for like as gold and ſiluer are tried in the fire, euen ſo are acceptable men in the fornace of aduerſitie. Beleue in God, and he ſhall helpe thee: order thy way a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right and put thy truſt in him: hold faſt his feare and grow therein.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 11.</note> Laugh no man to ſcorne in the heauines of his ſoule: for god (which ſeeth all things) is he that can bring downe, and ſet vppe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 11. 14.</note> Proſperitie and aduerſitie, life &amp; death, pouertie and riches, come all of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 11. 25.</note> When thou art in welfare, forget not aduerſitie: and when it goeth not well with thee, haue a good hope that it ſhal be better.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 12. 8. 9.</note> In proſperitie a friend ſhall not be kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen: and in aduerſitie an enemie ſhall not be hidd, for when a man is in welth it gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:11578:10"/> his enemies: but in heauines and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a man ſhall know his friend.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Aduoutrie.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus. 23. 18. 19.</note> A Man that breaketh wedlocke and regardeth not his ſoule, but ſayeth: Tuſh, who ſeeth me? I am compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed about with darkeneſſe, the walls couer me; no body ſeeth me: whom neede I to feare? The higheſt will not remember my ſinnes: He vnderſtandeth not that his eyes ſee all thinges, for all ſuch feare of men dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth away the feare of God from him, for he feareth onely the eyes of men, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth not that the eyes of the Lorde are clearer then the Sunne, beholding all the waies of men, and the ground of the deepe, and loking euen to mens heartes in ſecrete places.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 2. 16. 17. 18. 19.</note> An aduouterous woman geueth ſweete wordes, forſaketh the huſband of her youth and forgetteth the countenance of her god, for her houſe is inclined vnto death, and her paths vnto hel, all they that goe in vnto her come not againe, neither take they holde of the way of life.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 5. 3. 4 5.</note> Apply not thou thy ſelfe to the deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of a woman, for the lippes of an harlot
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:11578:10"/> are a dropping hony combe, and her throte is more gliſtering then oyle, but at the laſt ſhe is as bitter as wormewod, and her ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue as ſharpe as a two edged ſworde, her feete goe downe vnto death, and her ſtepps perſe thorough vnto hell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 6. 32. 33.</note> Whoſo committeth aduoutry with a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man he is a foole: and bringeth his life to deſtruction: he getteth him ſelfe alſo ſhame and diſhonor, ſuch as ſhall neuer be put out.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 22. 14.</note> The mouth of an harlot is a deepe pitt. wherein he falleth that the Lord is angry withall.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 23. 27. 28.</note> An whore is a deepe graue, and an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot is a narrow pit: ſhe lurketh like a theefe and bringeth vnto her ſuch men as be full of vice.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 9. 4. 5. 6</note> Looke not vppon a woman that is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of many men, leſt thou fall into her ſnares, caſt not thy mind vpon harlots in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny maner of thinge, leſt thou deſtroy both thy ſelfe and thine heritage.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 9. 11.</note> Sit not with an other mans wife by any meanes, lye not with her vpon the bedde: make no wordes with her at the wine, leſt thine heart conſent vnto her, and thou with thy bloud fall into deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 9. 9.</note> An aduouterous woman ſhall be troden
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:11578:11"/> vnder foote as mire, of euery one that goeth by the way.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 26. 9.</note> The whoredome of a woman may be knowen in the pride of her eies &amp; eye lidds.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Age.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 31.</note> AGe is a crowne of worſhip if it be founde in the way of righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 29.</note> The ſtrength of yonge men is their worſhip, and a gray head is an honour vnto the aged.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 11. 9.</note> Be glad (O thou yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g man) in thy youth, and lett thy heart be merry in thy yonge dayes: followe the wayes of thyne owne heart and the luſt of thyne eyes, but be thou ſure that God ſhall bring thee into iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for all theſe thinges.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">VViſ. 4. 8. 9</note> Age is an honorable thing: neuertheles it ſtandeth not in the length of time, nor in the multitude of yeares: but a mans wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is the gray heare, and an vndefiled life is the olde age.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus. 8. 6.</note> Thinke ſcorne of no man in his old age, for we waxe olde alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 8. 9.</note> Goe not from the doctrine of thyne el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: for they haue learned it of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for of them thou ſhalt learne vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſo that thou mayſt make anſwere
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:11578:11"/> in the time of neede.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 25. 3. 4. 5. 6.</note> If thou haſt gathered nothinge in thy youth, what wilt thou finde then in thine age.</p>
            <p>O how pleaſant a thing is it when gray headed men are diſcreete, and when the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders can geue good counſayle. O how com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a thing is wiſedom vnto aged men: yea vnderſtanding and counſayle is a glorious thing. The crowne of olde men is to haue much experience: and the feare of God is their worſhip.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Almes.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 3. 27. 28.</note> GEue vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, ſo ſhal thy barnes<note place="margin">Prou. 3. 10.</note> be filled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> plenteouſnes, &amp; thy preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhal flow ouer with ſweete wine. Withdrawe no good thinge from them that haue need ſo long as thine hand is able to do it. Say not vnto thy neighbour, go thy way and come again, to morow wil I geue thee, whereas thou haſt nowe to geue him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 14. 31</note> He that doth a pooreman wronge bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemeth his maker: but whoſo hath pity on the poore doth honour vnto God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 17. 5.</note> Whoſo laugheth the poore to ſcorne blaſphemeth his maker: and he that is glad of an other mans hurt ſhall not be vnpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:11578:12"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 4. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6.</note> My ſonne, defraude not the poore of his almes, and turne not away thyne eyes from him that hath neede. Deſpiſe not an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry ſoule, and defie not the poore in his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, greeue not the heart of him that is helpeleſſe: and withdraw not thy gift from the needefull. Refuſe not the prayer of one that is in trouble: turne not away thy face from the needy: caſt not thyne eyes aſide from the poore for any euill will, that thou geue him none occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpeak euil of thee: for if he complayne of thee in the bitternes of his ſoule, his prayer ſhall be heard, euen he that made him ſhall heare him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 10.</note> Be not faynt hearted when thou makeſt thy prayer, neither ſlacke in geuing of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. Reach thyne hand vnto the poore that God may bleſſe thee with plenteouſnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 29. 12. 13. 14.</note> Lay vp thyne almes in the hand of the poore, and it ſhall keepe thee from all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.</p>
            <p>A mans almes is a purſe with him and ſhall keepe a mans fauour as the apple of an eye, and afterward ſhall it ariſe, and pay euery man his rewarde vpon his head, It ſhal fight for thee agaynſt thy enemies bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the ſheelde of a gyant or ſpeare of the mighty.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:11578:12"/>
            <head>Ambition.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 4.</note> LAbour not vnto man for any Lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, neyther vnto the king for the ſeat of honour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6.</note> Make no labour to be made a Iudge, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it were ſo, that thou couldeſt mightely put downe wickednes, for if thou ſhouldeſt ſtand in awe of the preſence of the mighty, thou ſhouldeſt fayle in geuing ſentence.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 32. 1. 2. 3. 4.</note> If thou be made a ruler, pride not thy ſelf therein, but be thou as one of the people. Take diligent care for them and looke well thereto: and when thou haſt done all thy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſet thee downe that thou mayſt be merry with them, &amp; receaue a crowne of honour, talke wiſely and honeſtly, for wiſedom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth thee full well. Speake not where there is no audience, and powre not forth wiſedom out of time.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Battayle.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 24. 5. 6.</note> A Wiſe man is euer ſtrong: yea a man of vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding increaſeth of ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth for with diſcretion muſt warres be taken in hand, and where as many are that can geue good counſayle, there is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> victory.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti. 26. 29.</note> There be two thinges that greeue my
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:11578:13"/> heart, and the third is a diſpleaſure come vpon me. When an expert man of warre ſuffereth ſcarſeneſſe and pouertie, when men of vnderſtanding and wiſedom are not ſet by, and when one departeth from righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes vnto ſinne.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Bevvtie.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 31. 30.</note> AS for fauour it is deceitfull, &amp; bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is a vayne thing.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 9. 5. 8.</note> Beholde not a mayden that thou be not hurt in her bewtie.</p>
            <p>Turne away thy face from a bewtifull woman, and looke not vpon the faireneſſe of other: many a man hath periſhed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the bewtie of women, for thorough it the deſire is kindled as it were a fire.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">10.</note> Many a man wondering at the bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of a ſtraung woman, hath bene caſt out: for her wordes kindle as a fire.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 11. 2.</note> Commend not thou a man in his bewty, neither deſpiſe a man in his vtter appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 42. 12. 13.</note> Behold not euery bodies bewtie, &amp; haue not to much dwelling among women. For like as the worme and moth commeth out of the clothing, ſo doth wickedneſſe come of women.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:11578:13"/>
            <head>Boaſting and preſumption.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 27. 1.</note> MAke not thy boaſt of to morow, for thou knoweſt not what may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to day.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 5. 2. 3.</note> Follow not the luſt of thine owne heart in thy ſtrength, and ſay not: tuſh, how haue I had ſtrength, or who wil bring me vnder becauſe of my workes, for doubtles God ſhall aduenge it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 5. 5. 6. 7</note> Becauſe thy ſinne is forgeuen thee be not therefore without feare, neither heape one ſinne vpon an other, &amp; ſay not: tuſh the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Lord is great, he ſhall forgeue me my ſinnes be they neuer ſo many, for like as he is mercifull, ſo goeth wrath from him alſo, &amp; his indignation commeth down vpon ſinners. Make no tarying to turne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lord, &amp; put not of from day to day: for ſodenly ſhall his wrath come, &amp; in the time of vengeaunce he ſhall deſtroy thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>City.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 10.</note> WHen the iuſt are in welth the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie proſpereth: but when the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly haue the rule it decayeth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 29. 8.</note> Wicked people bring a citye in decay: but wiſe men ſet it vp againe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 10. 1.</note> When they that be in authoritie are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:11578:14"/> men of vnderſtanding, there the citie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpereth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Company.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 1. 10. 11. 15. 16.</note> MY ſonne conſent not vnto ſinners if they entiſe thee, and ſay come with vs: we will lay waite for bloud and lurke priuily for the innocent without a cauſe. My ſonne walke not with them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine thy foote from their way: for their feete runne to euill: and are haſty to ſhedde bloud.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 13. 20</note> He that goeth in the company of wiſe men ſhall be wiſe: but whoſo is a compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of fooles ſhall be hurt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 23. 20. 21.</note> Keepe not company with wine bibbers and riotous eaters of fleſh: for ſuch as be drunkards and riotous ſhall come to pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and he that is geuen to much ſleepe ſhal goe with a ragged coate.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 6. 35. 36. 37.</note> Stand with the multitude of ſuch elders as haue vnderſtanding, and conſent vnto their wiſedom with thyne heart, that thou mayſt heare all godly ſermons, and that the worthy ſentences eſcape thee not. And if thou ſeeſt a man of diſcreete vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, get thee ſoone vnto him, and let thy foote treade vpon the ſtepps of his doores.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:11578:14"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 8. 8.</note> Deſpiſe not the ſermons of ſuch elders as haue vnderſtanding, but acquaint thy ſelfe with the wiſe ſentences of them: for of them thou ſhalt learne wiſedom, and the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctine of vnderſtanding, and howe to ſerue great men without complaint.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 13. 1.</note> Whoſo toucheth pitch ſhalbe filed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: and he that is familiar with the proude ſhall cloth him ſelfe with pride.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2.</note> He taketh a burthen vppon him that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companieth a more honorable man then him ſelfe. Therefore keepe no familiaritie with one that is richer then thy ſelfe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Communication or talke.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 13. 3.</note> HE that keepeth his mouth, keepeth his life: but whoſo openeth his lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes to euill deſtroyeth him ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 15. 1. 2.</note> A ſofte anſwere putteth downe diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: but froward wordes prouoke vnto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. The tongue of ſuch as be wiſe vſeth knowledge aright, as for a fooliſh mouth it bableth out nothing but fooliſhnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 16. 26</note> A wiſe heart ordereth his mouth wiſely, and amendeth the doctrine in his lippes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 16. 28</note> A froward body cauſeth ſtryfe: and he that is a blabbe of his tongue maketh diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion among Princes.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:11578:15"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17. 27.</note> A wiſe man vſeth a few words, and he is a man of vnderſtanding that maketh much of his ſpirite: Yea a very foole when he hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth his tongue is counted wiſe: &amp; to haue vnderſtanding when he ſhutteth his lippes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 18. 4.</note> The wordes of a wiſe mans mouth are like deepe waters, and the well of wiſedom is like a full ſtreame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 21. 23</note> Whoſo kepeth his mouth &amp; his tongue, the ſame keepeth his ſoule from troubles.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29. 20.</note> If thou ſeeſt a man that is haſty to ſpeak vnaduiſed, thou mayſt truſt a foole more then him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 5. 2. Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 4. 24.</note> Where many words are, there men may heare fooles. In the tongue is wiſedom kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, ſo is vnderſtanding knowledge and learning in the talking of the wiſe, and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt, and in the workes of righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 5. 12. Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 5. 14.</note> Be ſwift to heare, but ſlowe and patient in geuing anſwere.</p>
            <p>Honour and worſhip is in a mans wiſe talking, but the tongue of the vndiſcreete is his owne deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 6. 5.</note> A ſweete word multiplieth friendes, and pacifieth them that be at variance, &amp; a tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful tongue wil be plenteous in a good man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 20. 7.</note> A wiſe man will hold his tongue till he ſee opportunitie, but a wanton and vndiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:11578:15"/> body ſhall regard no time.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 21. 16.</note> The talk of a foole is like an heauy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then by the way: but to heare a wiſe man ſpeake it is a pleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 27. 12.</note> If thou be among the vndiſcrete, keepe thy wordes vntill a conuenient time, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſuch as be wiſe ſpeake on hardly.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Conſtancy.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 5. 9. 10.</note> BE not caried about with euery winde, and go not into euery way, for ſo doth the ſinner that hath a double tongue. Stand faſt in the way of the Lord, be ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in thy vnderſtanding, abide by the word &amp; follow the word of peace &amp; righteouſnes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Correction.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 3. 11. 12.</note> MY ſonne deſpiſe not the chaſtening of the lord: neither faint when thou art rebuked of him. For whom the Lord loueth, him he chaſteneth, &amp; yet deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in him euen as a father in his own ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 10. 17</note> To take heede vnto the chaſtening of nurtour is the way of life: but he that refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to be refourmed deceiueth him ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 12. 1.</note> Whoſo loueth wiſedom will be content to be refourmed: but he that hateth to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued is a foole.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:11578:16"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 13. 18</note> He that thinketh ſcorne to be refourmed commeth to pouertie and ſhame: but whoſo regardeth correction ſhall come to honour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 13. 24</note> He that ſpareth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rod hareth his ſonne: but whoſo loueth him chaſteneth him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 15. 5.</note> A foole deſpiſeth his fathers correction, but he that taketh heede when he is repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſhall haue the more vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 15. 31</note> The eare that harkeneth to the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life, ſhall dwel among the wiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 15. 32</note> He that refuſeth to be refourmed, deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his owne ſoule: but he that ſubmitteth him ſelfe to correction is wiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17. 10.</note> One reprofe onely doth more good to him that hath vnderſtanding then a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſtripes vnto a foole.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 19. 29.</note> Puniſhments are ordayned for the ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſtripes for fooles backes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 23. 13. 14.</note> Withhold not correction from the child, for if thou beateſt him with the rodde, he ſhall not dye therof. If thou ſmite him with the rodde thou ſhalt deliuer his ſoule from hell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29. 15.</note> The rodde and correction miniſter wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but if a childe be not looked vnto, he bringeth his mother to ſhame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29. 17</note> Nurtour thy ſonne with correction, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11578:16"/> thou ſhalt be at reſt: yea he ſhall doe thee good at thyne heart.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 10. 26.</note> He that is wiſe and well nurtoured will not grudge when he is refourmed, and an ignorant body ſhall not come to honour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Countenaunce.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 13. 26. 27.</note> THe heart of a man chaungeth his countenaunce, whether it be in good or euill. A cheerefull countenaunce is a token of a good heart, for elſe it is an hard thing to know the thought.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 19. 27. 28.</note> One that hath vnderſtanding may be perceaued by the loke of his countenaunce.</p>
            <p>A mans garment, laughter, and going, declareth what he is.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Counſayle and counſellers.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 11. 14</note> WHere no good counſayle is, ther the people decay: but where as many are that can geue good counſayle, there is wealth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 12. 15.</note> Looke what a foole taketh in hande, he thinketh it well done: but he that is wiſe will be counſayled.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 22.</note> Vnaduiſed thoughts ſhal come to nought but where as men are that can geue good counſayle, there is ſtedfaſtnes.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:11578:17"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 23.</note> A ioyfull thing is it to a man when his counſayle is followed, and very pleaſant is a word ſpoken in due ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 16. 21</note> Whoſo hath a wiſe vnderſtanding ſhall be called to counſayle.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 18.</note> Wiſe counſayle in the heart of man is like a water in the deepe of the earth, and a man that hath vnderſtanding bringeth it forth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 20. 18</note> Thorough counſayle the thinges that men deuiſe goe forward, and with diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ought warres to be taken in hand.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 21. 5.</note> The deuiſes of one that is diligent bring plenteouſneſſe: but he that is vnaduiſed commeth vnto pouertie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 21. 30.</note> There is no wiſedom, there is no vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, there is no counſel againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 28. 2.</note> Becauſe of ſinn the land doth oft change her prince: but thorough men of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and wiſedom a realme endureth long.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 8. 17. 18</note> Take no counſell at fooles, for they loue nothing but the things that pleaſe them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues. Make no counſel before a ſtranger, for thou canſt not tell what will come of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> 37. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11. 12. 13.</note> Seeke no counſell at thy kinſman, and hide thy counſell from ſuch as bore thee no good will. Euery counſeler bringeth forth his counſell, neuertheles there is ſome that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:11578:17"/> counſeleth but for his owne profit. Beware of the counſeler and be aduiſed afore where to thou wilt vſe him, for he will counſell for him ſelfe, leſt he caſt the lot vpon thee and ſay vnto thee: thy way and purpoſe is good: and afterward he ſtand againſt thee &amp; looke what ſhall become of thee. Aſke no counſel at him that ſuſpecteth thee for an enemie, and hide thy counſel from ſuch as hate thee. Aſke no counſell at a woman concerning the thinges that ſhe longeth for: nor at a fearefull and fainthearted body, in matters of warre: nor at a marchaunt how deare he will cheape thy wares toward his: or at a bier of ſelling: or at an enuious man of than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes geuing: or at the vnmercifull of louing kindnes: or at an vnhoneſt man of honeſtie: or at the ſlouthful of working: or at an hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling which hath no houſe or profit of welth. Take no ſuch folkes to counſell: but be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to ſeke counſel at a vertuous man that feareth god: ſuch one as thou knoweſt to be a keeper of the commaundementes, which hath a mind after thine owne mind, &amp; is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for thee when thou ſtumbleſt. And holde thy counſell faſt in thine heart, for there is no man more faithfull to kepe it then thou thy ſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:11578:18"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 19. 8. 9.</note> Shew thy ſecretes neither to friend nor foe, and if thou haſt offended tel it not, for he ſhall harken vnto thee, and when he findeth opportunitie, he ſhall hate thee, and ſo ſhall he be alway about thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 37. 16.</note> Before all thy workes aſke counſayle firſt: and or euer thou doeſt any thinge be well aduiſed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Couetouſneſſe, looke liberalitie.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 10. 9.</note> THere is nothing worſe then a coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous man. There is not a more wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thing then to loue mony, &amp; why? ſuch one hath his ſoule to ſell, yet is he but filthy dounge while he liueth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 14. 9.</note> A couetous mans eie hath neuer enough in the porcion of wickedneſſe, vntill the tyme that he wither away, and hath loſt his owne ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 14. 3.</note> It becommeth not a couetous man and a nyggard to be rich: &amp; what ſhould a nyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard doe with gold.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 14. 4.</note> He that with all his carefulnes heapeth togither vnrighteouſly, gathereth for other folkes, and an other man ſhall make good cheere with his goodes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">10.</note> A nigard hath a wicked eye, he turneth away his face, and deſpiſeth his own ſoule.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:11578:18"/>
            <head>Curioſitie.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 25. 27.</note> LIke as it is not good to eate to much hony, euen ſo he that will ſearch out hie things it ſhall be to heauy for him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 3. 22. 23. 24. 25.</note> Seeke not out the things that are aboue thy capacitie, and ſearch not the ground of ſuch thinges as are to mighty for thee, but looke what God hath commaunded thee, thinke vpon that alway, and be not curious in many of his workes: for it is not neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for thee to ſee with thine eyes the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that are ſecret. Make not thou to much ſearch in ſuperfluous things, and be not cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in many of his works: for many thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges are ſhewed vnto the already, which be aboue the capacitie of men, the medling with ſuch hath begiled many a man, &amp; tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled their witts in vanitie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Daughter.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 22. 4. 5.</note> A Wiſe daughter is an heritage vnto her huſband: but ſhe that commeth to diſhoneſtie, bringeth her father in heauineſſe. A daughter that is paſt ſhame diſhonoureth both her father and her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, the vngodly ſhall regard her, but they both ſhall deſpiſe her.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:11578:19"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 26. 10. 11. 12.</note> If thy daughter be not ſhamefaſt, holde her ſtraitly, leſt ſhe abuſe her ſelfe through ouer much libertie, beware of all the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie of her eyes: and maruell not if ſhe doe againſt thee: like as one that goeth by the way and is thirſtie, ſo ſhall ſhe open her mouth and drinke of euery next water that ſhe may get. By euery hedge ſhall ſhe ſitte downe, and open her quiuer againſt euery arrow.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 42. 9. 10</note> The daughter maketh the father to watch ſecretely: and the carefulnes that he hath for her, taketh away his ſleepe: yea in the youth, leſt ſhe ſhould ouergrow him, &amp; when ſhe hath an huſband, leſt ſhe ſhould be hated: leſt ſhe ſhould be defiled in her vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginitie, or gotten with childe in her fathers houſe, or (when ſhe commeth to the man) leſt ſhe behaue her ſelfe not right, or conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue vnfruitefull.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 42. 11.</note> If thy daughter be wanton, keepe her ſtraitly, leſt ſhe cauſe thine enemies to laugh thee to ſcorne, and the whole citie to geue thee an euill report, and ſo thou be faine to heare thy ſhame of euery man, and be confounded before all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:11578:19"/>
            <head>Death.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 7. 1.</note> I Iudged thoſe that are deade to be more<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 4. 2. 3.</note> happy then thoſe that be aliue: yea him that is yet vnborne to be better at eaſe then they both, becauſe he ſeeth not the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable works that are done vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſunne.</p>
            <p>The day of death is better then the day of bir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">VViſ. 2. 23.</note> God created man to be vndeſtroyed: yea after the image of his owne likeneſſe made he him. Neuertheleſſe thorough enuie of the Deuill came death into the world, and they that holde of his ſide doe as he doth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">VViſ. 3. 1.</note> The ſoules of the righteous are in the hand of God, and the payne of death ſhall not touch them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 10. 11. 12.</note> Though the Phiſicion ſhew his help ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo long, yet in concluſion it goeth after this maner, to day a king to morrow dead. For when a man dieth he is the heire of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, beaſtes and wormes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 11. 28.</note> Prayſe no man before his death, for a man ſhall be knowen in his children.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 14. 14.</note> Worke thou righteouſnes before thy death, for in the hel there is no meat to find.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 14. 17.</note> All fleſh ſhall fade away like graſſe, and like a flouriſhing leaſe in a greene tree.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:11578:20"/> Some grow, ſome are caſt downe, euen ſo is the generation of all fleſh and bloud: one commeth to an ende an other is borne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 22. 11.</note> Make but litle weping becauſe of the dead: for he is come to reſt, but the life of the foole is worſe then the death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 36. 16. 17. 18. 19. 20. 21.</note> My ſonne bring forth thy teares ouer the dead and beginne to mourne, as if thou haddeſt ſuffered great harme thy ſelfe, and then couer his body after a conuenient ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and deſpiſe not his buriall. Enforce thy ſelfe to wepe, &amp; prouoke thy ſelfe to mourne and make lamentation expediently, &amp; that a day or two, leſt thou be euill ſpoken of, &amp; then comfort thy heauines, for of heauines commeth death, the heauines of the heart breaketh ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, take no heauines to heart, driue it away and remember the laſt thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, forget it not, for there is no turning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Thou ſhalt do him no good but hurt thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 41. 1. 2.</note> O death, how bitter is the remembrance of thee to a man that ſeeketh reſt and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in his ſubſtance and riches. Vnto the man that hath nothing to vexe him, &amp; that hath proſperitie in all things, yea vnto him that yet is able to receaue meate. O death, how acceptable and good is thy iudgement
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:11578:20"/> vnto the needefull, and vnto him whoſe ſtrength fayleth, and that is now in the laſt age, and that all thinges is full of care and fearefulneſſe, vnto him alſo that is in deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, and hath no hope nor pacience.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 41. 3. 4.</note> Be not thou afraid of death: remember them that haue bene before thee and that come after thee: this is the iudgement of the Lord ouer all fleſh. And why wouldeſt thou be againſt the pleaſure of the higheſt? whether it be ten hundred or a thouſand yeares, death aſketh not how long one hath liued.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Delicate liuing.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 21. 17</note> HE that hath pleaſure in bankettes ſhal be a poore man: whoſo deliteth in wine and delicates ſhall not be rich.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29. 21.</note> He that delicately bringeth vp his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant from a childe ſhall make him his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter at length.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 7. 2.</note> It is better to goe into an houſe of mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, then into a banketting houſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Diet.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 31. 19. 20.</note> O Howe well content is a wiſe man with a litle wine? ſo that in ſleepe thou ſhalt not be ſicke thereof, nor
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:11578:21"/> feele my paine. A ſweete holſom ſleepe ſhal ſuch a one haue and feele no inward greife. He riſeth vp betimes in the morning, and is well at eaſe in him ſelfe. But an vnſacia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eater ſleepeth vnquietly and hath ache and paine of the body.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 31. 21.</note> If thou feeleſt that thou haſt eaten to much, ariſe, goe thy way, caſt it out of thy ſtomacke, and take thy reſt, and it ſhall eaſe thee, ſo that thou ſhalt bring no ſickneſſe vnto thy body.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 37. 28. 29. 30.</note> Be not greedy in euery eating, and be not to haſty vpon all meates, for exceſſe of meates bringeth ſickneſſe, and gluttonie commeth at the laſt to an vnmeaſurable heate. Thorough ſurfet haue many a one periſhed: but he that dieteth him ſelfe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratly prolongeth his life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Diſſembling.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 10. 32.</note> DIſſembling lippes keepe hatred ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 11. 3.</note> The innocent dealing of the iuſt ſhal leade them: but the wickednes of ſuch as diſſemble ſhall be their own deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 9.</note> Thorough the mouth of the diſſembler is his neighbour deſtroyed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 13.</note> A diſſembling perſon wil diſcouer priuy
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:11578:21"/> thinges: but he that is of a faithfull heart will keepe counſell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 20.</note> The Lorde abhorreth them that be of a fayned heart, but he hath pleaſure in them that be of an vndefiled conuerſation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 12. 17</note> A true mouth is euer conſtant: but a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling tongue is ſoone chaunged.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 26. 28.</note> A diſſembling tongue hateth one that rebuketh him: and a flattering mouth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth miſchiefe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 19. 25.</note> A wicked man can behaue him ſelfe hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and can ducke with his head, and yet is but a deceauer within.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Doings of men, looke good men.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 16. 7.</note> VVHen a mans wayes pleaſe the Lorde, he maketh his very ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to be his friendes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 16. 1.</note> A man deuiſeth a way in his heart, but it is the Lorde that ordereth his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 17.</note> The path of the righteous is to eſchew euill, and whoſo looketh well to his wayes keepeth his owne ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 33.</note> The lottes are caſt into the lappe, but the ordering thereof ſtandeth all in the Lorde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 19. 22.</note> It is a mans worſhip to doe good, &amp; bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:11578:22"/> it is to be a poore man then a diſſembler.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou 20. 6.</note> Many ther be that would be called good doers: but where ſhall one finde a true faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 7.</note> Whoſo leadeth a godly and an innocent life is righteous: and happy ſhall his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be whom he leaueth behind him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 20. 9.</note> Who can ſay, my heart is cleane, I am innocent from ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 24.</note> The Lord ordereth euery mans going: how may a man then vnderſtand his owne way.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 21. 2.</note> Euery man thinketh his owne way to be right: but the Lord iudgeth the hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 21. 3.</note> To doe righteouſnes and iudgement is more acceptable to the Lord then ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 21. 5.</note> The iuſt deliteth in doing the thing that is right: but ouer the workers of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes hangeth deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 24. 16.</note> A iuſt man falleth ſeuen times and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vppe againe: but the vngodly fall into wickednes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 25. 21</note> If thine enemie hunger feede him, if he thirſt geue him drink: for ſo ſhalt thou heap coales of fier vpon his head, and the Lorde ſhall reward thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 13.</note> He that hideth his ſinnes ſhall not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper: but whoſo knowledgeth them &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:11578:22"/> them ſhall haue mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 28. 14</note> Well is him that ſtandeth in awe, as for him that hardeneth his heart he ſhall fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to miſcheefe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 28. 18.</note> Whoſo leadeth a godly and an innocent life ſhal be ſaued: but he that goeth froward wayes ſhall once haue a fall.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> 7. 7.</note> Iuſtifie not thy ſelfe before God, for he knoweth thy heart, and deſire not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted wiſe in the preſence of the King.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 36.</note> Whatſoeuer thou takeſt in hande, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the ende and thou ſhalt neuer doe amiſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Dreames.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 34. 1.</note> VNwiſe people begyle them ſelues with vaine and deceitfull hope, and fooles truſt dreames.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2.</note>Whoſo regardeth dreames is like him that will take holde of a ſhadow and follow after the winde: <note place="margin">3.</note> euen ſo is it with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearings of dreames.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 34. 5. 6.</note> Southſaying, witchcraft, ſorcerie and dreaming is but vanitie: like as when a woman trauaileth with childe, &amp; hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fantaſies in her heart. Where as ſuch viſions come not of God, ſet not thine heart vpon them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:11578:23"/>
            <head>Drunkenneſſe, looke more in vvine.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 19. 1.</note> A Labouring man that is geuen vnto drunkenneſſe ſhall not be rich, and he that maketh not much of ſmall thinges, ſhall fall by litle and litle.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 31. 25. 26.</note> Be not thou a wine bibber, for wine hath deſtroyed many a man. The fire proueth the hard iron, euen ſo doth wine proue the heartes of the proude when they be drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 31. 30.</note> Drunkenneſſe filleth the minde of the fooliſh with ſhame and ruine, miniſheth the ſtrength and maketh woundes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Enemie, looke more in loue and euill vvill.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 12. 10. 11. 12. 13.</note> TRuſt neuer thine enemie: For like as iron ruſteth, ſo doth his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, &amp; though he make much crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and kneeling, yet keepe well thy minde, and beware of him. Sette him not by thee, neither let him ſitte at thy right hande, leſt he turne him, get thee into thy place, take thy roome, and ſeke thy ſeate, and ſo thou at the laſt ſhalt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my wordes, and be pricked at my ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:11578:23"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">18.</note> An enemie is ſweete in his lippes, he<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 12. 17.</note> can make many good wordes, and ſpeake many good thinges, yea he can weepe with his eyes, but in his heart he imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth howe to throwe thee into the pitt: and if he may finde opportunitie, he will not be ſatisfied with bloud. If aduerſitie come vppon thee thou ſhalt finde him there firſt, and though he pretende to doe thee helpe, yet ſhall he vndermyne thee. He ſhall ſhake his heade and clappe his handes ouer thee for very gladneſſe, and while he maketh many wordes he ſhall diſguiſe his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Father and mother.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17. 21.</note> HE that begetteth a foole, begetteth his ſorrow: and the father of a foole can haue no ioy.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 19. 18</note> Chaſten thy ſonne while there is hope: but let not thy ſoule be moued to ſlaye him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 22. 6.</note> Teach a childe in his youth what way he ſhould goe: for he ſhall not leaue it when he is olde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 23. 24.</note> A righteous father is maruelous glad of a wiſe ſonne: and he that begetteth a wiſe childe, ſhall haue great pleaſure of him.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:11578:24"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 23.</note> If thou haue ſonnes, bring them vp in nourtour and learning, and holde them in awe from their youth vp.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 24. 25.</note> If thou haue daughters, keepe their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſhewe not thy face cherefull toward them. Mary thy daughter, and ſo ſhalt thou perfourme a weighty matter, but geue her to a man of vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 16. 1. 2. 3.</note> Delite not thou in the multitude of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly children: and haue no pleaſure in them if they feare not God. Truſt not thou to their life and regard not their labours. For one ſonne that feareth God, is better then a thouſand vngodly. And better is it for a man to die without children, then to leaue behinde him ſuch children as are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 30. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6.</note> Whoſo loueth his child holdeth him ſtil vnder correction, that he may haue ioy of him afterward, and that he grope not after his neighbours dores. He that teacheth his ſonne ſhall haue ioy in him, and neede not to be aſhamed of him among his acquainta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Whoſo enformeth and teacheth his ſonne, greeueth the enemie, and before his friends he may ioy of him, though the father dye, yet is he as though he were not dead, for he hath left one behinde him that is like him in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:11578:24"/> his life, he ſawe him and had ioy in him, and was not ſory in his death, neither was he aſhamed before his enemies, for he left be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him an auenger againſt his enemies, and a good doer vnto the friendes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">7.</note> He that chaſteneth his childe bindeth the wounds togither, that his heart may feare euery word.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">8.</note> An vntamed horſe will be hard, and awanton childe will be wilfull.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 30. 9. 10. 11. 12. 13.</note> If thou bring vp thy ſonne delicately, he ſhall make thee afraid: &amp; if thou play with him he ſhall bring thee to heauines. Laugh not with him leſt thou wepe with him alſo, and leſt thy teeth be ſet on edge at the laſt. Geue him no libertie in his youth, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe not his folly, bowe downe his necke while he is yong, hit him vpon the ſides, while he is yet but a childe, leſt he waxe ſtubburne and geue no more force of thee, and ſo ſhalt thou haue heauines of ſoule. Teach thy childe and be diligent therein, leſt it be to thy ſhame.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Feare of the Lord.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 1. 15. 16. 17.</note> THe feare of the Lorde is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of wiſedom.</p>
            <p>The feare of the lord is the right
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:11578:25"/> ſeruice of God that preſerueth and iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the heart and geueth mirth &amp; gladneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">18.</note> Whoſo feareth the Lorde ſhall be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, and when he hath neede of comfort he ſhall be bleſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">20.</note> The feare of the Lord is wiſedom that maketh rich &amp; bringeth all good with her.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">22.</note> The feare of the Lorde is the crowne of wiſedom, and geueth plenteous peace and health.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">24.</note> The feare of the Lorde is the roote of wiſedom, and her braunches are long life.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">26.</note> The feare of the Lord driueth out ſinne: for he that is without feare can not be made righteous, and his wilfull boldneſſe is his owne deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 2. 9.</note> O ye that feare the Lord take ſure hold of his mercy, ſhrinke not away from him, that ye fall not.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">10.</note> O ye that feare the Lorde beleue him and your reward ſhall not be empty.</p>
            <p>O ye that feare the Lord put your truſt in him: and mercy ſhall come vnto you for pleaſure.</p>
            <p>O ye that feare the Lorde ſet your loue vpon him, and your hearts ſhal be lightned.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">11.</note> Conſider the olde generations of men, o ye children &amp; marke them well: was there
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:11578:25"/> euer any confounded that put his truſt in the Lord? Who euer continued in his feare<note place="margin">12.</note> and was forſaken? Or whom did he euer deſpiſe that called faith fully vpon him? for God is gracious and mercifull, he forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſinnes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of trouble, &amp; is a defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of all them that ſeeke him in the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">16.</note> They that feare the Lorde will not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt his word, and they that loue him will keepe his commaundements.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">17.</note> They that feare the Lord will ſeeke out the things that are pleaſaunt vnto him, and they that loue him will fulfill his lawe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">18.</note> They that feare the Lord will prepare their hearts and humble their ſoules in his ſight.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">19.</note> They that feare the lord keepe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements and will be pacient till they ſee him ſelfe, ſaying: better it is for vs to fal into the handes of the Lorde, then into the handes of men:<note place="margin">21.</note> for his mercy is as great as him ſelfe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Folly.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 1. 32.</note> THe proſperitie of fooles ſhalbe their owne deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou 2. 21.</note> The wiſe ſhal haue honour in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, but ſhame is the promotion y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fooles
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:11578:26"/> ſhall haue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 10. 23.</note> A foole doth wickedly and maketh but a ſporte of it: but wiſedom ruleth the man that hath vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 12. 16.</note> He that hath vnderſtanding doth hyde wiſedom, but an vndiſcrete foole telleth out his fooliſhnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 14. 7.</note> See that thou medle not with a foole in whom thou perceaueſt to be no knowledge.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 14. 8.</note> The wiſedom of him that hath vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, is to take heede vnto his wayes, but the fooliſhnes of the vnwiſe deceiueth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 14 9.</note> Fooles make but a ſporte of ſinne, but there is a fauourable loue among the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 18. 7.</note> A fooles mouth is his owne deſtruction, and his lippes are the ſnare of his owne ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 26. 3.</note> Vnto the horſe belongeth a whip, to the aſſe a bridle, and a rodde to the fooles back.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 26. 12</note> If thou ſeeſt a man that is wiſe in his owne conceit, there is more hope of a foole then in him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 26. 17.</note> Whoſo goeth by and medleth with other mens ſtrife, he is like one that taketh a dog by the eares.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 26.</note> He that truſteth in his owne heart is a foole: but he that dealeth wiſely ſhall be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:11578:26"/> ſafe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 10. 11.</note> The wordes of a wiſe mans mouth are gracious: but the lippes of a foole will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The beginning of his talking is fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and laſt word of his mouth is ſtarke madneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 21. 14.</note> The heart of a foole is like a broken veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, he can keepe no wiſedom.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 22. 13.</note> Talke not much with a foole, and go not with him that hath no vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 27. 13.</note> The talking of fooles is abomination, and their ſporte is voluptuouſneſſe and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nurtour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Fortune commonly called in deede nothing elſe but the prouidence of God.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 4. 14.</note> SOme one commeth out of priſon and is made a King: and an other which is borne in the kingdom commeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to pouertie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 9. 10.</note> In running it helpeth not to be ſwift, in battayle it helpeth not to be ſtrong: to fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it helpeth not to be wiſe: to richeſſe it helpeth not to be ſubtil: to be had in fauour it helpeth not to be cunning, but that all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in time and fortune.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:11578:27"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 11. 5.</note> Many tyrauntes haue bene faine to ſitte downe vpon the earth, and the vnlikly haue worne the crowne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 11. 6.</note> Many mighty men haue bene brought lowe: and the honorable haue bene deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into other mens handes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 11. 11. 12.</note> There is ſome man that laboureth, and the more he werieth him ſelfe, the leſſe he hath. Againe ſome man is ſlouthfull, hath nede of help, wanteth ſtrength &amp; hath great pouertie, and Gods eye loketh vpon him to good, ſetteth him from his low eſtate, &amp; lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vp his head: ſo that many men maruell at him and geue honour vnto God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 11. 21.</note> Continue not in the workes of ſinners, but put thy truſt in God, and bide in thine eſtate: for it is but an eaſy thing in the ſight of God to make a poore man rich, and that ſodenly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 20. 9.</note> Some man getteth a fall for being to proude, and ſome commeth to worſhip from low eſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 37. 18. 19. 20. 21.</note> Some man is apt and well enſtructed in many things, and yet very vnprofitable vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him ſelfe. Some man there is that can geue wiſe and prudent counſell, and yet is he hated, and continueth a beggar: for the grace is not geuen him of God to be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:11578:27"/> An other is robbed of all wiſedome, yet is he wiſe vnto him ſelfe, and the fruit of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is commendable in his mouth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Friendſhip.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 17. 17</note> HE is a friend that alway loueth, and in aduerſitie a man ſhall know who is his brother.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 18. 19</note> A brother though he be greeued with offence, yet is he more worth then a very ſtrong caſtell: and they that holde togither are like the barre of a pallace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 18. 24.</note> A man that loueth his friendes will be companable with them: and ſome friende ſticketh faſter to a man then his brother.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 27. 6.</note> Faythfull are the woundes of a louer, but the kiſſes of an enemy are cruell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 27. 9.</note> Balme &amp; ſweete incenſe make the heart merry: ſo is the ſweete counſell of a mans friende that agreeth to his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 27. 10.</note> Thine own friend and thy fathers friend ſee thou forſake not: but goe not into thy brothers houſe in time of trouble, for better is a friende at hande then a brother a farre of.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 4. 9. 10. 11. 12.</note> Two are better then one, for they may well enioye the profite of their labour. For if one of them fall, his companion
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:11578:28"/> helpeth him vp againe: But woe is him that is alone: for if he fall he hath not an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to helpe him vppe. Againe, when two ſleepe togither they are warme, but howe can a body be warme alone? one may be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome, but two may make reſiſtance. A threefold gable is not lightly broken.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 6. 6.</note> Holde friendſhip with many, neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe haue but one counſeller of a thouſand.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 6. 7 8. 9. 10. 11. 12</note> If thou getteſt a friend proue him firſt, and be not haſty to geue him credence, for ſome man is a friend but for a time, &amp; will not abide in the day of trouble. And there is ſome friend that turneth to enmitie, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth part againſt thee, and if he knowe any hurt by thee he telleth it out. Againe ſome friend is but a companion at the table, and in the day of neede he continueth not. But a ſure friend will be vnto thee euen as thine owne ſelfe, and deale faithfully with thy houſhold folke. If thou ſuffer trouble and aduerſitie he is with thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 6. 13.</note> Depart from thyne enemies, yea and beware of thy friendes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 6. 14. 15. 16. 17.</note> A faithfull friende is a ſtronge defence, whoſo findeth ſuch one findeth a treaſure. A faithfull friend hath no peare, the weight of golde and ſiluer is not to be compared to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:11578:28"/> the goodnes of his faith. A faithfull friende is a medicine of life, and they that feare the Lorde ſhall finde him. Whoſo feareth the Lorde ſhall proſper with friendes, and as he is him ſelfe ſo ſhall his friend be alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 18.</note> Geue not ouer thy friend for any good, nor thy faithfull brother for the beſt golde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 9. 12.</note> Forſake not an olde friend, for the newe ſhall not be like him. A newe friend is new wine: let him be olde and thou ſhalt drinke him with pleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 19. 15.</note> Tell thy friend his fault leſt he be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt, and ſay: I haue not done it, or if he haue ſpoken that he doe it no more.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 27. 17. 18.</note> Loue thy friend and binde thy ſelfe in faithfulnes with him, but if thou bewrayeſt his ſecretes thou ſhalt not get him againe: For like as the man is that deſtroyeth his enemie, ſo is he alſo that dealeth falſely in the friendſhip of his neighbour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 37. 4.</note> There is ſome companion which in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie reioyceth with his friend: but in the time of trouble he taketh part againſt him.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Giftes or revvardes.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 17. 8.</note> A Reward is a precious ſtone vnto him that hath, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but vnto whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it turneth, it maketh him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:11578:29"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17. 13.</note> Whoſo rewardeth euill for good, the plague ſhall not depart from his houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17. 23.</note> The vngodly taketh gifts out of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to wreſt the waies of iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 19. 6.</note> The multitude hangeth vpon great men: and euery man fauoureth him that geueth rewardes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 21. 14</note> A priuy rewarde pacifieth diſpleaſure, &amp; a gift in the boſome ſtilleth furiouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 25. 13.</note> Whoſo maketh great boaſtes and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth nothing, is like cloudes &amp; winde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out raine.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>God.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 3. 5. 6 7.</note> PUt thy truſt in God with all thine hearte, and leane not vnto thyne owne witte: in all thy wayes haue reſpect vnto him, and he ſhall order thy goinges. Be not wiſe in thine owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite, but feare the Lorde and depart from euill.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 5. 21.</note> Euery mans wayes are open in the ſight of the Lorde, and he pondereth all their goings.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 15. 3.</note> The eyes of the Lorde looke on euery place beholding both the good and badde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 11.</note> The hell with her paine is knowen vnto
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:11578:29"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord: how much more then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearts of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 16. 1. 2. 3.</note> A man may well purpoſe a thing in his heart, but the anſwere of the tongue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of the Lord.</p>
            <p>A man thinketh all his wayes to be cleane, but it is the Lorde that iudgeth the minde. Commit thy workes vnto the Lord and loke what thou deuiſeſt it ſhall proſper.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 22.</note> Say not thou I will recompence euill: but put thy truſt in the Lorde and he ſhall defend thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29. 25.</note> He that feareth men ſhall haue a fall: but whoſo putteth his truſt in the Lord is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out daunger.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 8. 12.</note> Though an euill perſon offend an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred times, &amp; God defer, geuing him long life: yet am I ſure that it ſhall goe wel with them that feare God, becauſe they haue him before their eyes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 12. 13.</note> Feare God and keepe his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for that toucheth all men, for God ſhall iudge all workes, and ſecrete thinges whether they be good or euill.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 13. 8. Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 13. 13. Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cus 15. 11. 12. 13.</note> Submit thy ſelfe vnto God and waite vpon his hande.</p>
            <p>Loue God all thy life long, and call vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him in thy neede.</p>
            <p>Say not thou, it is the Lordes fault that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:11578:30"/> I am gone by, for thou ſhalt not doe the thing that God hateth. Say not thou, he hath cauſed me to doe wronge, for he hath no neede of the vngodly. God hateth all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination of errour, and they that feare God will loue none ſuch.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 16. 11. 12.</note> Mercy and wrath is with him: he is both mighty to forgeue, &amp; to poure out diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: like as his mercy is greate, euen ſo is his puniſhment alſo, he iudgeth a man according to his workes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 32. 23. 24.</note> In all thy workes put thy truſt in God from thy whole heart, for that is the keping of the commaundements: whoſo beleueth Gods word taketh heede to the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, and he that putteth his truſt in the Lord ſhall want nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 33. 1.</note> There ſhall no euill happen vnto him that feareth God: but when he is in tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Lorde ſhall deliuer him and keepe him from euill.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 33. 12.</note> Like as the clay is in the potters hand, and all the ordering thereof at his pleaſure: ſo are men alſo in the handes of him that made them, ſo that he may geue them as li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him beſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Good men and euill.</head>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:11578:30"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 2. 21. 22.</note> THe iuſt ſhall dwell in the lande, and they that be perfect ſhall remaine in it: but the vngodly ſhall be rooted out of the lande and the wicked doers ſhall be rooted out of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 3. 33.</note> The curſe of the Lord is in the houſe of the vngodly: but he bleſſeth the dwellings of the righteous.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 3. 31. 32.</note> Followe not a wicked man and chooſe none of his wayes: for the Lord abhorreth the froward, but his counſell is among the righteous.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 4. 14. 15. 16.</note> Come not in the path of the vngodly, and walk not in the way of the wicked, abhorre it and goe not therin, depart aſide and paſſe ouer by it: for they can not ſlepe except they haue firſt done ſome miſchief: neither take they any reſt except they haue firſt done ſome harme.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 4. 18. 19.</note> The path of the rightwiſe ſhineth as the light, that is euer brighter and brighter vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the perfect day: but the way of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly is as the darkeneſſe, they knowe not where they fall.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 10. 16</note> The righteous laboureth to doe good: but the vngodly vſeth his encreaſe vnto ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 10. 25.</note> The vngodly paſſeth when the tempeſt commeth: but the righteous remaineth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:11578:31"/> ſure for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 10. 30.</note> The righteous ſhall neuer be ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen: but the vngodly ſhall not remaine in the land.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 11. 6.</note> The righteouſneſſe of the iuſt ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them: but the wicked ſhall be taken in their owne vngodlineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 18.</note> The labour of the vngodly proſpereth not: but he that ſoweth righteouſnes ſhall receaue a ſure rewarde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 19.</note> Like as righteouſneſſe bringeth life, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo to cleaue vnto euill bringeth death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 12. 7.</note> God ouerturneth the eſtate of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and they ſtand not: but the houſe of the righteous ſhall ſtand ſtedfaſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 12. 21.</note> There ſhall no misfortune happen vnto the iuſt, but the vngodly ſhall be filled with miſerie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 13. 21</note> Miſchiefe followeth vppon ſinners, but the righteous ſhall haue a good reward.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 11.</note> The houſe of the vngodly ſhall be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen: but the tabernacle of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhall flouriſh.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 15. 9.</note> The way of the vngodly is an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto the Lorde: but whoſo followeth righteouſnes, him he loueth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 29.</note> The Lord is farre from the vngodly, but he heareth the prayer of the righteous.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:11578:31"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">VViſ. 5. 16. 17.</note> The righteous ſhall liue for euermore, their rewarde alſo is with the Lorde, and their remembrance with the higheſt. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhall they receaue a glorious kinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and a bewtifull crowne at the Lordes hand: for with his right hand ſhall he couer them, and with his owne holy arme ſhall he defend them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 40. 9. 10</note> Death, bloudſheding, ſtrife, and ſworde, oppreſſion, hunger, deſtruction, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, theſe thinges are created againſt the vngodly, and for their ſakes came the floud alſo.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Health and ſickneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 18. 14.</note> A Good ſtomack driueth away a mans diſeaſe, but when the ſpirite is vexed who may abide it?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 30. 14. 15. 16.</note> Better is the pore being whole &amp; ſtrong, then a man to be rich and not to haue his health. Health &amp; welfare is aboue all gold, and a whole body aboue all treaſure. There is no riches aboue a ſound body, and no ioy aboue the ioy of the heart. Death is better then a wretched life, and eternall reſt better then continuall ſickneſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Hovvſe and huſbandry.</head>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:11578:32"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 24. 27.</note> FIrſt make vp thy worke that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and looke well vnto that which thou haſt in the fielde, and then builde thine houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 24. 3. 4</note> Thorough wiſedome is an houſe buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and with vnderſtanding is it ſett vppe. Thorough diſcretion ſhal the chambers be filled with all coſtly and pleaſant riches.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 27. 23.</note> See that thou knowe the number of thy cattell thy ſelf, and looke well to thy flocks: for riches abide not alway, and the crowne endureth not for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 27. 25.</note> The hay groweth, the graſſe commeth vp, and herbes are gathered in the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 27. 26.</note> The lambes ſhall cloth thee, and for thy goates thou ſhalt haue money to thy huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry: thou ſhalt haue goates milke e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to feede thee, to vphold thy houſhold and to ſuſtaine thy maidens.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 15.</note> Let no laborious worke be tedious vnto thee, neither the huſbandry which the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty hath created.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 22.</note> If thou haue cattell looke well to them, and if they be for thy profite, keepe them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 48.</note> The encreaſe of the earth vpholdeth all thing: yea the King him ſelfe is maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by huſbandry.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:11578:32"/>
            <head>Houſevvife.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 31. 10. ad finem.</note> WHoſo findeth an honeſt faithfull woman, ſhe is much more worth then pearles. The heart of her huſband may ſafely truſt in her, ſo that he ſhall fall in no pouertie. She will doe him good, and not euill all the dayes of her life. She occupieth woll and flaxe, and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth gladly with her handes. She is like a marchaunts ſhip that bringeth her vittails from farre. She is vp in the night ſeaſon to prouide meate for her houſhold, and foode for her maidens. She conſidereth land and byeth it, and with the fruite of her handes ſhe planteth a vineyarde. She girdeth her loynes with ſtrength, and courageth her armes. And if ſhe perceaue that her houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wifery doth good, her candell goeth not out by night. She laieth her fingers to the ſpin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and her hand taketh hold of the diſtaffe. She openeth her hand to the poore, yea ſhe ſtretcheth forth her handes to ſuch as haue neede. She feareth not that the cold of win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhall hurt her houſe, for all her houſhold folke are clothed with ſcarlet. She maketh her ſelfe fine ornamentes, her clothing is white ſilke and purple. Her huſband is
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:11578:33"/> much ſet by in the gates. When he ſitteth among the rulers of the lande. She maketh cloth of ſilke and ſelleth it, and deliuereth girdles vnto the marchaunt. Strength and honour is her clothing, and in the latter daye ſhe ſhall reioyce. She openeth her mouth with wiſedom, and in her tongue is the lawe of grace. She looketh well to the wayes of her houſholde, and eateth not her breade with idleneſſe. Her children ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe and call her bleſſed, and her huſband ſhall make much of her. Many daughters there be that gather riches togither, but thou goeſt aboue them all. As for fauour it is deceitfull, and bewtie is a vayne thinge. But a woman that feareth the Lorde, ſhe is worthy to be prayſed. Geue her of the fruite of her hands, and let her owne works prayſe her in the gates.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Iudge and iudgement.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17. 15.</note> THe Lord hateth as well him that iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth the vngodly as him that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth the innocent.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 18. 5.</note> It is not good to regard the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the vngodly, or to put backe the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 18. 13.</note> He that geueth ſentence in a matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:11578:33"/> he heare it, is a foole and worthy to be confounded.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 22. 22.</note> See that thou robbe not the poore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is weake, and oppreſſe not the ſimple in iudgement, for the Lorde him ſelfe will defende their cauſe, and doe vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence vnto them that haue vſed violence.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 24. 11.</note> Deliuer them that goe vnto death, and are ledde away to be ſlayne, and be not neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent therein: if thou be able to doe them good.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 24. 23. 24. 25.</note> It is not good to haue reſpect of any perſon in iudgement. He that ſayeth to the vngodly thou art righteous, him ſhal the people curſe: yea the comminaltie ſhall abhorre him. But they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke the vngodly, in them doth God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite, and a rich bleſſing ſhall come vppon them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 29. 7.</note> The righteous conſidereth the cauſe of the poore, but the vngodly regardeth no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 31. 8. 9.</note> Be thou aduocate for the dumme, and ſtand in iudgement thy ſelfe to ſpeake for all ſuch as be ſuccourleſſe in this tranſitory worlde. Open thy mouth, defende the thing that is lawfull and right, and the cauſe of the poore and helpeleſſe.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:11578:34"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 3. 16. 17.</note> I ſawe vnder the Sunne vngodlines in the ſtede of iudgment, and iniquitie in ſtede of righteouſneſſe. Then I thought in my minde: God ſhall ſeparate the righteous from the vngodly, and then ſhall be the time and iudgement of all counſell and workes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 5. 7.</note> If thou ſeeſt the poore to be oppreſſed and wrongfully dealt withall, ſo that equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and the right of the law is wreſted in the lande, maruell not thou at ſuch a thing: for one great man kepeth touch with an other, and the mighty men are in authoritie ouer the poore.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 5. 5. VViſ. 1. 1. 2</note> See that thou iuſtifie the ſmal and great alike.</p>
            <p>O ſet your affection vpon righteouſnes, ye that be iudges of the earth. Haue a good opinion of the Lorde, and ſeeke him in the ſingleneſſe of heart, for he will be founde of them that tempt him not, and appeareth vnto ſuch as put their truſt in him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">VViſ. 6. 2. 3 4. 5. 6. 7.</note> O learne ye that be iudges of the earth. Geue eare ye that rule the multitudes, and delite in much people. For the power is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you of the Lorde, and the ſtrength from the higheſt: which ſhall trie your workes, and ſerch out your imaginations. How that ye being officers of his kingdom, haue not
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:11578:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> executed true iudgement: haue not kept the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> righteouſnes: nor walked after the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of God. Horrible and that right ſoone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> appeare vnto you: for an hard iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they haue that bare rule. Mercy is graunted vnto the ſimple, but they that be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> authoritie ſhall be ſore puniſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 4. 9. 10.</note> Deliuer him that ſuffereth wrong from the hand of the oppreſſour, and be not faynt hearted when thou ſitteſt in iudgement. Be mercifull vnto the fatherleſſe as a father, and be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of an huſband vnto their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo ſhalt thou be as an obedier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſonne of the higheſt, and he ſhall loue thee more then thy mother doth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 10. 1.</note> A wiſe iudge will order his people with diſcretion: and where a man of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding beareth rule, there goeth it well.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 10. 2. 3.</note> As the iudge of the people is him ſelfe, euen ſo are his officers: and looke what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of man the ruler of the citie is, ſuch are they that dwell therein alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 10. 21.</note> Greate is the iudge and mighty in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, yet is there none greater then he that feareth God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 11. 7. 8.</note> Condemne no man before thou haue tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out the matter, and when thou haſt made inquiſition, then reforme righteouſly. Geue
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:11578:35"/> no ſentence before thou haſt hearde the cauſe, but firſt let men tell out their tales.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Knovvledge and learning.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 1. 5.</note> BY hearing the wiſe, man ſhall come by more wiſedom.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6.</note> If thou cryeſt after wiſedom, and calleſt for knowledge: If thou ſeekeſt after her as after money, and diggeſt for her as for treaſure, then ſhalt thou vnderſtand the feare of the Lord, and finde the knowledge of God: For it is the Lorde that geueth wiſedom, out of his mouth commeth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 2. 10. 11.</note> If wiſedom enter into thyne heart and thy ſoule delite in knowledge, then ſhal cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell preſerue thee, and vnderſtanding ſhall keepe thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 10. 13.</note> In the lipps of him that hath vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a man ſhall finde wiſedom.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 15.</note> An ignoraunt body beleueth all things: but whoſo hath vnderſtanding looketh well to his goings.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 18. 15.</note> A wiſe heart laboureth for knowledge, and a prudent eare ſeeketh vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 22. 17. 18.</note> My ſonne bowe downe thine eare, &amp; har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto the words of wiſedom: apply thy mind vnto my doctrine, for thou ſhalt be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:11578:35"/> if thou keepe it in thy heart, &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe it in thy mouth that thou maiſt put thy truſt in the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 1. 18.</note> Where much wiſedom is, there is alſo great trauell and diſquietnes, and the more knowledge a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath, the more is his care.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 1. 8.</note> All things are ſo hard to be knowen that no man can expreſſe them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 3. 11.</note> God hath planted ignoraunce alſo in the hearts of men, that they ſhould not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the grounde of his workes which he doth from the beginning to the ende.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 20. 29.</note> Wiſedom that is hid, &amp; treaſure that is horded vp, what profit is in them both? Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is he that kepeth his ignoraunce ſecret, then a man that hideth his wiſedom.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 21. 21.</note> Learning is vnto a wiſe man a iewell of golde, and like an armelet vpon his right arme.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 21. 13.</note> The knowledge of the wiſe ſhall flowe like water that runneth ouer, and his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell is like a fountaine of life.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>King or Prince.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 28.</note> THe encreaſe and proſperitie of the commons is the Kings honour: but the decay of the people is the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Prince.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:11578:36"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 10</note> When the prophecie is in the lippes of the King, his mouth ſhall not goe wrong in iudgement.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 12.</note> It is a great abomination when Kings are wicked, for a Kings ſeate ſhould be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den vp with righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 13.</note> Righteous lippes are pleaſaunt vnto Kings, and he that ſpeaketh the truth ſhall be beleued.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 16. 14</note> The Kings diſpleaſure is a meſſenger of death: but a wiſe man will pacifie him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 15.</note> The cherefull countenaunce of the king is life: and his louing fauour is as the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning dewe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 17. 7.</note> Speech of authoritie becommeth not a foole: much leſſe a lying mouth then beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a Prince.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 19. 12.</note> The Kings disfauour is like the roring of a lyon: but his friendſhip is like the dew vpon the graſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 20. 2.</note> The King ought to be feared as the ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of a lyon: Whoſo prouoketh him to anger offendeth againſt his owne ſoule.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 20. 8.</note> A King that ſitteth in the throne of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and looketh well about him, driueth away all euill.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 26.</note> A wiſe Kinge deſtroyeth the vngodly, and bringeth the wheele ouer them.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:11578:36"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 28.</note> Mercy and faithfulneſſe preſerue the King: and with louing kindneſſe his ſeate is holden vp.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 21. 1.</note> The Kinges heart is in the hande of the Lorde, like as are the riuers of water, he may turne it whither ſo euer he will.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 24. 21. 22.</note> My ſonne, feare thou the Lorde and the Kinge, and keepe no company with them that ſlide backe from his feare: for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction ſhal come ſodenly, and who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the aduerſity that may come from them both.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou 25. 1.</note> It is the honour of God to kepe a thing ſecrete, but the Kinges honour is to ſearch out a thing.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 25. 2.</note> The heauen is high, the earth is deepe, and the Kings heart is vnſearchable.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 25. 3. 4.</note> Take the droſſe from the ſiluer and there ſhall be a cleane veſſell thereof. Take away vngodlines from the Kinge, and his ſeate ſhall be eſtabliſhed with righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 15.</note> Like as the roring of a lyon and an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry beare, euen ſo is an vngodly Prince o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the poore people.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 16.</note> Where the prince is without vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, there is great oppreſſion &amp; wronge: but if he be ſuch a one as hateth couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he ſhall long raigne.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:11578:37"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 29. 4.</note> With true iudgement the King ſetteth vp the land: but if he be a man that oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the people with gatheringes, he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it vpſide downe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29. 14.</note> The ſeat of the King that faithfully iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the poore ſhall continue ſure for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 31. 4.</note> It is not for Kinges, it is not (I ſay) for Kings to drinke wine, nor Princes ſtrong drinke: for there is no ſecrete where drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes raineth, leſt they being drunken for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the lawe, and peruert the iudgement of all poore mens children.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 10. 15. 16.</note> Woe be vnto thee (O land) whoſe King is but a child, &amp; whoſe princes are earely at their bankettes. But well is thee (O land) whoſe King is come of nobles, and whoſe Princes eate in due ſeaſon for neceſſitie and not for luſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Labour, looke more in ſlouthfulneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 3. 9.</note> WHat hath a man elſe (that doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing) but werines &amp; labour? For as touching the trauell and carefulneſſe which God hath geuen vnto men, I ſee that he hath geuen it them to be exerciſed in it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 3. 13.</note> All that a man eateth and drinketh, yea,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:11578:37"/> whatſoeuer a man enioyeth of all his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, that ſame is a gift of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 3. 22.</note> I perceaue that there is nothing better for a man then to be ioyfull in his labour: for that is his portion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Lavve of God and man.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 13. 14.</note> THe law is a wel of life vnto the wiſe, that it may keepe him from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſnares of death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 25. 7. 8 9.</note> Be not haſty to goe to the lawe, leſt happly thou doe ſome offence after the ſtrife be ended, whereby thy neighbour put thee to ſhame. Handle thy matter with thy neighbour him ſelfe, and diſcouer not an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans ſecret, leſt when men heare ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it turn to thy diſhonour, and leſt thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill name doe not ceaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 28. 4.</note> They that forſake the law praiſe the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly: but ſuch as kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law abhorre them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 28. 7.</note> Whoſo keepeth the lawe is a childe of vnderſtanding: but he that is a companion of riotous men ſhameth his father.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 9.</note> He that turneth away his eare from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the lawe, his prayer ſhall be abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 29. 9.</note> If a wiſe man goe to lawe with a foole, (whether he deale w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him frendly or rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:11578:38"/> he getteth no reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29. 18.</note> When the worde of God is not pree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, the people periſh but well is him that keepeth the lawe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 30. 5. 6.</note> All the wordes of God are pure and cleane, for he is a ſhield vnto all them that put their truſt in him. Put thou nothing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his wordes, leſt he reproue thee and thou be found a liar.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 6. 38.</note> Let thy minde be vpon the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and be earneſtly occupied in his lawes, ſo ſhall he eſtabliſh thy heart and geue thee wiſedom at thine owne deſire.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 8. 14.</note> Goe not to lawe with the iudge, for he will iudge according to his owne honour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 19. 24.</note> A crafty ſubtell man can be wiſe, but he is vnrighteous, and with giftes he wraſteth the open and manifeſt law.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Lending and borovving.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 29. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6.</note> WHoſo will ſhewe mercy let him lende vnto his neighbour: and he that is able let him keepe the commaundement. Lende vnto thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in time of his neede, and pay thou thy neighbour againe in due ſeaſon. Keepe thy worde, and deale faithfully with him, and thou ſhalt alway finde the thing that is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:11578:38"/> for thee. There haue ben many that when a thing was lent them, reckened it to be founde, and made them trauaile and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour that had helped them. While they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue any thing they kiſſe the handes of ſuch as geue them, for their neighboures good they humble their voyce: but when they ſhould pay againe, they keepe it back, and geue euill wordes, and make many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes by reaſon of time: and though he be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet geueth he ſcarſe the halfe againe, and reckeneth the other to be found. And if he with holde not his money, yet hath he an enemy of him, and that vndeſerued. He pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him with curſing and rebuke, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him euill wordes for his good deede.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 29. 7. 8. 9. 10.</note> There be many one which are not glad for to lende, not becauſe of euill, but they feare to leſe the thing that they lende: yet haue thou pacience with the ſimple, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde not mercy from him. Helpe the poore for the commaundements ſake, and let him not goe empty from thee becauſe of his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity. Leſe thy money for thy brother and neighboures ſake, and bury it not vnder a ſtone where it ruſteth and corrupteth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Liberalitie.</head>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:11578:39"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 11. 24</note> SOme man geueth out his goodes and is the richer: but the nigard (hauing enough) wil depart from nothing, and yet is euer in pouertie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 25.</note> He that is liberall in geuing ſhall haue plenty: and he that watereth ſhall be wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red alſo him ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 26.</note> Whoſo hordeth vp his corne ſhalbe cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed among the people: but bleſſing ſhall light vpon his head that geueth foode.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 18. 16.</note> Liberalitie bringeth a man to honour &amp; worſhip, and ſetteth him among great men.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 33.</note> Be liberal vnto al men liuing, yet let not but doe good euen vnto them that are dead.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 31. 23.</note> Whoſo is liberal in dealing out his meat, many men ſhall bleſſe him, and prayſe him with their lippes, and the ſame is a ſure to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of his loue and faithfulneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 40. 17.</note> Friendlineſſe and liberalitie is the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and bleſſing of God, is like a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe and garden of pleaſure: ſuch mercy alſo and kindnes endureth for euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Loue and euill vvill.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 10. 12.</note> EVill wil ſtirreth vp ſtrife, but loue co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth the multitude of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 17.</note> Better is a meſſe of pottage with loue, then a fatte oxe with euill will.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:11578:39"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 23. 6. 7</note> Eate thou not with the enuious, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not his meate: for he doth as a man that preſcribeth a meaſure to thee in his heart. He ſayeth vnto thee, eate and drinke, where as his heart is not with him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 24. 17. 18.</note> Reioyce not thou at the fall of thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and let not thine heart be glad when he ſtumbleth, leſt the Lorde (when he ſeeth it) be angry and turne his wrath from him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 26. 23.</note> Venimous lipps and a wicked heart are like a potſhard couered with ſiluer droſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 26. 24. 25.</note> An enemie ſhall be knowen by his tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and in the meane ſeaſon he imagineth miſchiefe, but when he ſpeaketh faire beleue him not, for there are ſeuen abominations in his heart.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 26. 26.</note> Whoſo keepeth euill will ſecretely to doe hurte, his malice ſhall be ſhewed before the whole congregation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 8. 7.</note> Be not glad of the death of thine enemy, but remember that we muſt dye all the ſort of vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 25. 1.</note> Three thinges there are that my ſpirite fauoureth, which be alſo allowed before God and man. The vnitie of brethren, the loue of neighbours, a man and wife that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree well togither.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:11578:40"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 28. 3. 4. 5. 6.</note> A man that beareth hatred againſt an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, how dare he deſire forgeuenes of God? If he that is but fleſh beareth hatred and keepe it, who will intreate for his ſinnes? Remember the ende, and let enimitie paſſe, which ſeeketh death and deſtruction, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide thou in the commaundements.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Liuing.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 30. 7. 8 9.</note> TWo thinges haue I required of thee (Lorde) that thou wilt not deny me before I die. Remoue from me vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and lyes: geue me neither pouertie nor riches, onely graunt me a neceſſary liuing, leſt if I be to full I deny thee and ſay: Who is the Lord? And leſt I being conſtrayned through pouertie, fall vnto ſtealing &amp; take the name of God in vayne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 29. 23.</note> The chiefe thing that kepeth in thy life, is water and breade, clothing and lodging to couer thy ſhame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 29. 24.</note> Better it is to haue a poore liuing in a mans owne houſe, then delicat fare among the ſtraunge.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 29. 25. 26. 27.</note> Be it litle or much that thou haſt, holde thee content withall, and thou ſhalt not be blamed as a vagabound, for a miſerable life is it to goe from houſe to houſe, and where a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:11578:40"/> man is freinded he dare not ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his mouth. Though one be lodged and haue meate and drinke, yet ſhall he be taken as vnworthy, and heare many bitter rough wordes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 32. 21. 22.</note> Geue not thy ſelfe into a laborious ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery way, and beware of thy children, and take heede of them that be thine owne hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 33. 18. 19. 20.</note> Geue not thy ſonne and wife, thy brother and friend, power ouer thee, while thou li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, and geue not away thy ſubſtance and good to an other, leſt it repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thee that thou be faine to begge therefore thy ſelf. As long as thou liueſt and haſt breath, let no man chaunge thee: for better it is that thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren doe pray thee, then that thou ſhouldeſt be faine to looke in their handes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 33. 22.</note> At y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> time when thou ſhalt end thy daies, &amp; finiſh thy life, diſtribute thine inheritance</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 39. 26. 27.</note> All thinges neceſſary for the life of man are created from the beginning: water, fire, yron and ſalte, meale, meate and hony, milke and wine, oyle and clothing. Al theſe thinges are created for the beſt to the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. But to the vngodly ſhal all theſe things be turned to hurt and harme.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Maners.</head>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:11578:41"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 22.</note> A Faire woman without diſcrete ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, is like a ringe of golde in a ſwines ſnowte.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 23. 1. 2 3.</note> When thou ſitteſt at the table to eate with a Lorde, order thy ſelfe manerly with the things that are ſet before thee. Meaſure thine appetite, and if thou wilt rule thine owne ſelfe, be not ouer greedy of his meat, for meate beguileth and deceaueth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 14.</note> Put not forth thy ſelfe in the preſence of<note place="margin">Prou. 25. 5. 6.</note> the King, and preaſe not into the place of great men. Better is it that it be ſayd vnto thee, come vp higher, then thou to be put lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer in the preſence of the Prince, whom thou ſeeſt with thine eyes.</p>
            <p>Make not many wordes when thou art among the elders.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 21. 23.</note> A foole will peepe in at the window in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe, but he that is well nourtered will ſtand without. A fooliſh man ſtandeth harkening at the doore, but he that is wiſe will be aſhamed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 31. 12. 13. 14. 15. 16. 17. 18.</note> If thou ſitte at a great mans table, open not thy mouth wide vpon it, and make not many wordes, lay not thine hand vpon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that thine eye ſeeth, and ſtriue not with him in the diſhe. Ponder by thy ſelfe what thy neighbour would fayne haue, and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:11578:41"/> be diſcrete in euery poynt. Eate the thing that is ſet before thee manerly as it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a man, and eate not to much leſt thou be abhorred. Leaue thou of firſt of all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of nurtour, leſt thou be he whom no man may ſatisfie, which may turne to thy decaye. When thou ſitteſt amonge many men, reache not thyne hande out firſt of all.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 32. 8. 9. 10. 11. 12. 13. 14.</note> Thou yong man ſpeak that becommeth thee, and that is profitable, and yet ſcarſe when thou art twiſe aſked, comprehende much with fewe wordes, in many things be as one that is ignorant, geue eare and hold thy tongue withall. If thou be among men of higher authoritie, deſire not to compare thy ſelfe vnto them: and when an elder ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, make not thou many wordes therein. Stand vp betimes, and be not the laſt, but get thee home ſoone, and there take thy pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime, and doe what thou wilt, ſo thou doe none euill &amp; defie no man, but for all things geue thankes vnto him that haue made thee, and repleniſhed thee with his goodes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 41. 19.</note> Be aſhamed to lye with thine elbowes vpon the bread.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 42. 8.</note> Be ſhamefaſt and well manered in deed, ſo ſhall euery man fauour thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:11578:42"/>
            <head>Marchaunt.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 27. 2.</note> THere be two maner of things, which<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 26. 30.</note> me thinke to be hard and perellous. A marchaunt cannot lightly keepe him from wrong, neither a Tauerner him ſelfe from ſinne.</p>
            <p>Like as a nayle in the wall ſticketh faſt betwene two ſtones, euen ſo doth ſinne ſtick betwixt the byer and the ſeller.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Meaſure and weight.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 11.</note> A True meaſure &amp; a true balance are the Lordes iudgement: he maketh all weights.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 10.</note> To vſe two maner of weightes or two maner of meaſures, both theſe are abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable vnto the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 14.</note> It is nought, it is nought (ſayth he that byeth any thinge) but when he commeth to his owne houſe then he boaſteth of his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyworth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 23.</note> The Lorde abhorreth two manner of weightes, and a falſe balance is an euill thing.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Mercy.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 3. 3. 4.</note> LEt mercy and faythfulneſſe neuer goe from thee: binde them about thy necke,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:11578:42"/> and write them in the tables of thine heart. So ſhalt thou finde fauour and good vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in the ſight of God and men.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 17.</note> He that is mercifull doth him ſelfe a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite, but whoſo hurteth his neighbour is a tyraunt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 22.</note> He that putteth his truſt in the Lord lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to be mercifull.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 21. 21.</note> Through mercy and faith are ſinnes<note place="margin">Prou. 15. 1.</note> purged: and through the feare of the Lord doth euery one eſcape euill.</p>
            <p>Whoſo followeth righteouſneſſe and mercy, findeth both life, righteouſnes and honour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 34.</note> Let not them that wepe be without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, but mourne with ſuch as mourne. Let it not greeue thee to viſite the ſicke, for that ſhall make thee to be beloued.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 18. 12.</note> The mercy that a man hath, reacheth to his neighbour, but the mercy of God is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all fleſh.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 28. 4.</note> He that ſheweth no mercy to a man that is like him ſelfe, how dare he aſke forgeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his ſinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 35. 2.</note> Whoſo is mercifull and geueth almes, geueth a thankfull offering.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:11578:43"/>
            <head>Myrth and ioye.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 30.</note> A Mery hart is the life of the body: but rancour conſumeth away the bones.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 15. 13</note> A mery hart maketh a cheerefull countenaunce: but an heuy hearte compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth a man to ſigh.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17. 22.</note> A mery hearte maketh a luſtie age: but a ſorowfull minde drieth vp the bones.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 25. 19.</note> Like as the moth hurteth a garment, and a worme a tree: ſo doth the heauineſſe of a man hurt the hearte.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 7. 3.</note> Grauitie is better then to laugh: for when the countenance is heauy, the hearte is refourmed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 7. 4.</note> The hearte of the wiſe is in the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning howſe, but the hearte of the fooliſh is in the howſe of myrth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 8. 15.</note> I commend gladnes, becauſe a man hath no better thing vnder the ſunne then to eate and drinke &amp; to be merry: for that ſhall he haue of his labour all the daies of his life, which God geueth him vnder the Sunne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 9. 17.</note> Let thy myrth be in the feare of God, let the remembrance of God be in thy minde, and let all thy talking be in the commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the higheſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 30. 21. 22. 23. 24. 25.</note> Geue not ouer thy minde vnto heauineſſe:
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:11578:43"/> and vexe not thy ſelfe in thine owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile. The ioye and cheerefulneſſe of the hearte, is the life of man, and a mans glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is the prolonging of his dayes. Loue thine owne ſoule and comfort thine hearte: as for ſorowe and heuineſſe driue it farre from the, for heuineſſe hath ſlaine many a man, and bringeth no profit: zeale and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſhorten the daies of the life: carefulneſſe and ſorow bring age before the time, vnto a mery hearte euery thing hath a good taſte that he eateth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Name or fame.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 10. 7.</note> THe memoriall of the iuſt ſhall haue a good reporte: but the name of the vngodly ſhall ſtinke.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 30.</note> Like as the clereneſſe of the eyes reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the hearte, ſo doth a good name feede the bones.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 7. 1.</note> A good name is more worth then a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ointment.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 41. 12.</note> Labour to get thee a good name, for that ſhal continue ſurer by thee, then a thouſand great treaſures of golde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 41. 13.</note> A good life hath a nomber of dayes, but a good name endureth for euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Neighbour.</head>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:11578:44"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 3. 29. 30.</note> INtend no hurt vnto thy neighbour, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he doth dwell in reſt by thee, ſtriue not lightly with any without a cauſe, where as he hath done thee no harme.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 23.</note> Whoſo deſpiſeth his neighbour doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe, but bleſſed is he that hath pity on the poore.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 24.</note> The ſoule of the vngodly wiſheth euill, and hath no pitie vpon his neighbour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 22. 28.</note> Thou ſhalt not remoue the land marke which thy forelders haue ſet.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 25. 16.</note> Withdrawe thy foote from thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours houſe, leſt he be weary of thee and ſo abhorre thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 25. 17.</note> Whoſo beareth falſe witneſſe againſt his neighbour, he is a very clubbe, a ſword, and a ſharpe arrow.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 4. 23. 24.</note> Be not aſhamed of thy neighbour in his aduerſitie, and keepe not backe thy counſell when it may doe good.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 6. 1.</note> Be not thy neighbours enemye for thy friendes ſake: for whoſo is euill ſhall be the heire of rebuke and diſhonour, and whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beareth enuie and a double tongue, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 19. 10.</note> If thou haſt heard a worde againſt thy neighbour, let it be dead within thee, and be ſure thou ſhalt haue no harme thereby.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:11578:44"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 19. 14. 15.</note> Reproue thy neighbour that he keepe his tongue: and if he haue ſpoken that he ſay it no more, tell thy neighbour his fault, for oft times an offence is made, and geue not credence to euery word.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 22. 23.</note> Be faithfull vnto thy neighbour in his pouertie, that thou mayſt reioyce with him alſo in his proſperitie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 28. 2.</note> Forgeue thy neighbour the hurt that he hath done to thee, and ſo ſhall thy ſinnes be forgeuen thee alſo when thou prayeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 31. 31.</note> Rebuke not thy neighbour at the wine, and deſpiſe him not in his mirth, geue him no deſpitefull wordes, and preaſſe not vpon him with contrary ſayings.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 34. 23.</note> Whoſo robbeth his neighbour of his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, doth as great ſinne as though he ſlew him to death.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Obedience and rule.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 29. 2.</note> WHen the righteous haue the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hand, the people are in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, but when the vngodly beareth rule, then the people mourne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 8. 2.</note> I muſt keepe the Kinges commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; the oth that I haue made vnto God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 10. 19.</note> Wiſh the King no euill in thy thought, and ſpeake no hurt of the rich in thy priuy
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:11578:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:11578:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:11578:46"/> chamber: for a birde of the ayre ſhal betray thy voyce, and with her fethers ſhall ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray thy wordes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 4. 7.</note> Humble thy ſoule vnto thy elder, &amp; bow downe thy head to a man of worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 4. 25.</note> Withſtande not the face of the mighty, and ſtriue thou not againſt the ſtreame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 26. 1.</note> Like as ſnow is not meete in Sommer, nor raine in harueſt, euen ſo is worſhip vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemely for a foole.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Pacience.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 14. 11.</note> THe pacient abiding of the righteous ſhall be turned to gladneſſe: but the hope of the vngodly ſhall periſh.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 29.</note> He that is pacient hath much vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: but he that is ſoone diſpleaſed, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoketh fooliſhneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 18.</note> An angry man ſtirreth vp ſtrife: but he that is pacient ſtilleth diſcord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 32.</note> A pacient man is better then one ſtrong: &amp; he that can rule him ſelfe, is more worth then he that winneth a citie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 19. 11.</note> A wiſe man can put of diſpleaſure: and it is his honour to let ſome faultes paſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 25. 14.</note> With pacience is a Prince pacified: and with a ſoft tongue is rigorouſnes broken.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Pouertie.</head>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:11578:46"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 19. 17</note> HE that hath pitie vpon the poore lendeth vnto the Lorde: and looke what he layeth out it ſhall be payed him againe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 21. 13.</note> Who ſo ſtoppeth his eares at the crying of the poore: he ſhall cry him ſelfe and not be hearde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 22. 16</note> Who ſo doth a poore man wrong to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe his owne richeſſe, and giueth vnto the riche to pleaſe him, at the laſt commeth to pouertie him ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 3</note> One poore man oppreſſing an other by violence is like a continuall raine that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth the fruite.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 6.</note> A poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leading a godly life, is better then the riche that goeth in froward waies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 27.</note> He that geueth vnto the poore, ſhall not lacke: but he that turneth away his eyes from ſuche as be in neceſſitie, ſhall ſuffer greate pouertie him ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 10. 32.</note> The poore is honoured for his faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: but the riche is had in reputation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his goodes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 10. 33.</note> He that ordereth him ſelfe honeſtly in pouertie, how much more ſhall he behaue him ſelfe honeſtly in richeſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 13. 20. 21. 22. 23. 24.</note> The wild aſſe is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s pray in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, euen ſo are poore men the meat of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:11578:47"/> riche. Like as the proude may not away with lowlineſſe, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo do the riche abhorre the poore. If a riche man fall his frendes ſet him vp againe. But when the poore fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth his acquainta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce forſake him. If a riche man fall into errour he hath many helpers, he ſpeaketh proude wordes, and yet men iuſtifie him. But if a poore man go wrong he is puniſhed: yea though he ſpeake wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, yet can it haue no place. When the riche man ſpeaketh, euery man holdeth his tongue: and loke what he ſaieth, they praiſe it vnto the cloudes. But if the poore man ſpeake, they ſay: what fellow is this? and if he do amiſſe they ſhall deſtroy him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 21. 5.</note> The prayer of the poore goeth out of the mouth and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vnto the eares of God, and his defence ſhall come and that haſtly.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Prayſe.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 27. 2.</note> LEt another man prayſe thee and not thyne owne mouth: yea other folkes lippes and not thyne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 27. 14.</note> He that is to haſty to praiſe his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour aboue meaſure, ſhall be taken as one that geueth him an euill reporte.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 27. 21.</note> Siluer is tried in the moulde, and golde in the fornace, and ſo is a man when he is openly praiſed to his face.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:11578:47"/>
            <head>Prayer.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 18. 21. 22.</note> Let not to praye alway, and ſtande not in feare to be refourmed vnto death, for the rewarde of God endureth for euer. Before thou prayeſt prepare thy ſoule, and be not as one that tempteth God. Think vpon the wrathfull indignation that ſhall be at the ende, and the howre of vengeance when he ſhall turne away his face.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 35. 13. 14. 15. 16.</note> The Lorde heareth the prayer of the oppreſſed. He diſpiſeth not the deſire of the fatherleſſe, nor the widdow, when ſhe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth out her prayer before him. Doth not God ſee y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teares that runne down y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chekes of the widdow? or heareth he not her com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint ouer ſuche as make her to weepe? from her cheekes do the teares go vp into heauen, and the Lorde which heareth them doth accept them: whoſo ſerueth God after his pleaſure ſhall be accepted: &amp; his prayer reacheth vnto the cloudes. The prayer of him that humbleth him ſelfe goeth thorow the cloudes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Prieſtes.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 29. 30. 31.</note> FEare the Lord with all thy ſoule, and honour his miniſters, loue thy maker with all thy ſtrength, and forſake not
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:11578:48"/> his ſeruauntes: Feare the Lorde with all thy ſoule, and honour his prieſtes. Geue them their portion of the firſt fruites and increaſe of the earth like as it is commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thee: and reconcile thy ſelf of thy negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence with the litle flocke: geue them the ſhoulders, and their appointed offeringes and firſtlinges.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 14. 11.</note> My ſonne, do good to thy ſelfe of that thou haſt, and geue the Lorde his due of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feringes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 35. 8. 9. 10.</note> Geue God his honour with a cheerefull hearte, and keepe not backe the firſtlinges of thy handes. In all thy giftes ſhew a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull countenaunce, and hallowe thy tithes vnto God with gladneſſe. Geue vnto God according as he hath enriched and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thee. And looke what thy hande is able, geue with a cheerefull eye: for the Lorde recompenceth and geueth the ſeuen times as much againe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Phiſician and Phiſike.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 38. 1. 2. 3. 4.</note> HOnour the Phiſician, honour him becauſe of neceſſity. God hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him: (for of the higheſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth medecine) and he ſhall receiue giftes of the king. The wiſedom of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phiſician bringeth
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:11578:48"/> him to greate worſhippe, and in the ſight of great men of this worlde, he ſhall be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably taken. The Lorde hath created me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine of the earth, and he that is wiſe will not abhorre it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 38. 9. 10.</note> My ſonne deſpiſe not this in thy ſicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but pray vnto the Lorde, and he ſhall make the whole.</p>
            <p>Leaue of from ſinne, and order thy handes aright, clenſe thine hearte from all wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 38. 15.</note> He that ſinneth before his maker ſhall fall into the handes of the Phiſician.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Pride and lowlineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 2.</note> WHere Pride is there is ſhame alſo and confuſion: but where as is lowlineſſe there is wiſedome.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 25.</note> The Lord will breake downe the howſe of the proude, but he ſhal make faſt the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the widdow.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 33.</note> The feare of the Lord is the right ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of wiſedome: and lowlineſſe goeth before honour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 5.</note> The Lorde abhorreth all ſuch as be of a proude heart, his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d is againſt their hand, and they ſhall not eſcape as innocentes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 18. 19.</note> Preſumpteouſnes goeth before deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:11578:49"/> and after a proud ſtomack there followeth a fal. Better it is to be of humble mind with the lowly, then to diuide the ſpoyles with the proud.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 18. 12.</note> After pride commeth deſtruction, and honour after lowlineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 21. 4.</note> A preſumptuous looke, a proud ſtomack, and the plowing of the vngodly is ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 21. 24.</note> He that is proude and preſumptuous is called a ſcornefull man which in wrath dare worke maliciouſly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 21. 5.</note> The ende of lowlineſſe and the feare of God is richeſſe, honour, proſperitie and health.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 25.</note> He that is of a proud ſtomack and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feare, ſtirreth vp ſtrife: but he that put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his truſt in the Lord ſhal be wel fedde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 29. 23.</note> After pride commeth a fall, but a lowly ſpirite bringeth great worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 3. 19.</note> The greater thou art the more humble thy ſelfe in all thinges, and thou ſhalt finde fauour in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 10. 7. Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 10. 13. 14.</note> Pride is hatefull before God and man.</p>
            <p>The beginning of mans pride is to fall away from God, &amp; why? his heart is gone from his maker, for pride is the original of all ſinne. Whoſo taketh hold therof ſhall be filled with curſinges, and at the laſt it ſhall
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:11578:49"/> ouerthrow him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 10. 15. 16.</note> God hath deſtroyed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeats of proud prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and ſet vp the meeke in their ſtede. God hath withered the rootes of the proud hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and planted the lowly among them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 10. 18.</note> God hath deſtroyed the name of the proud, and left the name of the humble of minde.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Richeſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 10. 2.</note> TReaſures that are wickedly gotten profit nothing: but righteouſnes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuereth from death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 10. 22</note> The bleſſing of the Lorde maketh rich men: as for careful trauaile it doth nothing thereto.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 11. 4.</note> Richeſſe helpe not in the day of venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: but righteouſnes deliuereth from death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 13. 7.</note> Some men are rich though they haue nothing: ſome men are poore hauing great richeſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 11. 28</note> He that truſteth in his richeſſe ſhal haue a fall: but the righteous ſhall floriſh as the greene leafe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 13. 11.</note> Vaynely gotten goodes are ſoone ſpent: but they that be gathered togither with the hand ſhall increaſe.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:11578:50"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 13. 22.</note> The richeſſe of the ſinner is laide vp for the iuſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 20.</note> The poore is hated eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his own neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures: but the riche hath many frendes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 15. 16.</note> Better is a litle with feare of the Lord, then greate treaſure with ſorow.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 16. 8.</note> Better is it to haue a litle thinge with righteouſneſſe, then greate rentes wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully gotten.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 18. 10 11.</note> The name of the Lorde is a ſtrong ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtell, the righteous flieth vnto it, and is in ſauegarde: but the riche mans goodes are his ſtrong holde: yea he taketh them, for an high wall rounde aboute him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 19. 4.</note> Riches make many frends: but the poore is forſaken of his neighbour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 21. 6.</note> Who ſo hordeth vp riches with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of his tongue, he is vain and a foole, &amp; like vnto them that ſeeke their own death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 23. 4. 5.</note> Take not ouer great trauaile and labour to be riche, beware of ſuch a purpoſe. Why wilt thou ſet thine eye vpon the thinges which ſodenly vaniſh away.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 28. 8.</note> He that by vſurie and vniuſt gaines ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth richeſſe, he ſhall lay them in ſtore for a man that will pitie the poore.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 11.</note> The riche man thinketh him ſelfe to be wiſe: but the poore that hath vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:11578:50"/> can perceiue him well enough.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 28. 20.</note> A man that dealeth faithfully ſhall be filled with bleſſinges: and he that maketh to muche haſte for to be riche ſhall not be vngiltie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 22.</note> He that wilbe riche all to ſoone, hath an euill eye, and conſidereth not that pouertie ſhall come vpon him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 5. 19.</note> He that loueth money will neuer be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied with money: &amp; who ſo deliteth in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe ſhall haue no profit thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 5. 11.</note> A labouring man ſleepeth ſwetely, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be litle or much that he eateth: but the abundance of the riche will not ſuffer him to ſleepe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 5. 12. 13. 14.</note> Yet is there a ſore plage which I haue ſeene vnder the Sunne, (namely) riches kept to the hurte of him that hath them in poſſeſſion: for ofte times they periſh with his great miſery and trouble, and if he haue a childe it getteth nothing. Like as he came naked out of his mothers wombe ſo goeth he thither againe: &amp; carieth nothing away with him of all his labour. This is a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable plage that he ſhall go away euen as he came.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 5. 18.</note> Vnto whome ſo euer God geueth riches, goods, &amp; power, he giueth it him to enioy it,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:11578:51"/> to take it for his porcion, and to be refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of his labour: this is the gyft of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 5. 1.</note> Truſt not vnto thy richeſſe, and ſay not, tuſh I haue enough for my life, for it ſhall not helpe thee in the time of vengeance and temptation.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 5. 8.</note> Truſt not in wicked riches, for they ſhal not helpe in the day of puniſhment &amp; wrath.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 31. 1. 2.</note> Trauaile and carefulneſſe for richeſſe, take away the ſleepe, and maketh the fleſh to conſume. When one lyeth and taketh care he awaketh euer vppe, like as a great ſicknes breaketh the ſleepe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 31. 3.</note> The rich hath great labour in gathering his richeſſe togither, &amp; then with the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of his richeſſe he taketh his reſt and is refreſhed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Seruaunt.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 17. 2.</note> A Diſcrete ſeruaunt ſhall haue more rule then the ſonnes that haue no wiſedom, and ſhal haue like heritage with the brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 27. 18.</note> Whoſo keepeth his figge tree ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the fruites thereof: euen ſo he that wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vpon his maſter ſhall come to honour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 20.</note> Whereas thy ſeruaunt worketh truely, intreate him not euill, nor the hireling that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:11578:51"/> is faithfull vnto thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 21.</note> Loue a diſcrete ſeruaunt as thine owne ſoule: defraude him not of his libertie, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leaue him a poore man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 33. 23. 24. 25. ad finem cap.</note> The fodder, the whippe, and the burthen belongeth vnto the Aſſe: Meate, correction, and work, vnto thy ſeruaunt. If thou ſet thy ſeruaunt to labour thou ſhalt finde reſt: but if thou let him goe idle, he ſhall ſeeke liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. The yoke and the whip boweth downe the hard necke, but tame thou thy euill ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt with bondes and correction, ſend him to labour that he goe not idle, for idleneſſe bringeth much euill. Set him to worke, for that belongeth vnto him, and becommeth him well. If he be not obedient, binde his feete: but doe not to much vnto him in any wiſe, and without diſcretion doe nothing. If thou haue a faithful ſeruaunt, let him be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee as thine owne ſoule: intreate him as a brother, for in bloud haſt thou gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. If thou haue a ſeruaunt holde him as thy ſelfe, If thou intreat him euill and keepeſt him hard, and makeſt him to be proude and to runne away from thee, thou canſt not tell what way thou ſhalt ſeeke him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 34. 23.</note> He that defraudeth the labourer of his hyre is a bloud ſhedder.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:11578:52"/>
            <head>Shame, whereof we ought to be aſhamed and whereof not.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 41. 17. 18. 19. 20. 21. 22. 23.</note> BE aſhamed of whoredome before fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother. Be aſhamed of leaſing before the Prince and men of authoritie: Of lying before the iudge and ruler: Of offence before the congregation and people: Of vnrighteouſneſſe before a companion and frende. Of theft before thy neighboures. Be aſhamed to lie with thine elbowes vpon the breade: Be aſhamed to looke vpon harlottes: Be aſhamed to turne away thy face from thy frendes: Be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to take and not to geue: Be aſhamed alſo to looke vpon anothers mans wife, &amp; to make any trifling words with her maiden, or to ſtande by her bedſide: Be aſhamed to vpbraide thy frende when thou geueſt any thing, caſt him not in the teeth withall.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 42. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8</note> Of theſe thinges be not aſhamed. Of the lawe of God: Of the couenaunt of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: To bring the vngodly from his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe vnto righteouſnes: and to make him a good man: To deale faithfully w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy neighbour and companion: To diſtribute the heritage vnto thy frends: To be dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to kepe true meaſure &amp; weight: To be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent whether thou getteſt much or litle: To
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:11578:52"/> deale truly with temporall goods in bying and ſelling: To bring vp thy children with diligence: To correct an euill ſeruant: To keepe that thine is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an euill wife: To ſet a locke where many handes are: what thou deliuereſt and geueſt out to be kept, to tell it and to wey it: To write vp all thy out ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and receauing: To enfourme the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerned &amp; vnwiſe: Of the aged that are iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of the yong: if thou be diligent in theſe thinges, truely thou ſhalt be learned and wiſe and accepted of all men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Sonne, and the dutie of children tovvard their parentes.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 1. 8. 9.</note> MY ſonne heare thy fathers doctrine, &amp; forſake not the lawe of thy mother: for that ſhall bring grace vnto thy heade, and ſhall be as a chaine about thine necke.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 6. 20. 21. 22.</note> My ſonne keepe thy fathers commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and forſake not the lawe of thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: put them vp together in thine hearte, &amp; binde them about thy necke: that they may leade thee where thou goeſt, preſerue thee when thou arte a ſleepe, and that when thou awakeſt thou maieſt talke of them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> A wiſe ſonne maketh a glad father: but an vndiſcrete ſonne is an heauineſſe vnto
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:11578:53"/> his mother.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 13. 1.</note> A wiſe ſonne will harken to his fathers warning: but he that is ſcornfull will not heare when he is reproued.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 35.</note> A deceitfull ſonne ſhall haue no good: but a diſcrete ſeruaunt ſhall doe full well, and his way ſhall proſper.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 17. 6.</note> Childers children are worſhip vnto the elders: and the fathers are the honour of the children.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17. 25.</note> An vndiſcrete ſonne is a greefe vnto his father, and an heauineſſe vnto his mother.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 19. 26.</note> He that hurteth his father or ſhutteth out his mother, is a ſhameful and an vnworthy ſonne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 11.</note> A childe is knowne by his conuerſation whether his workes be pure and right.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 20.</note> Whoſo curſeth his father and mother, his light ſhall be put out in the middeſt of darkeneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 23. 22.</note> Geue eare vnto thy father that begate thee, and deſpiſe not thy mother when ſhe is olde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 23. 25.</note> Doe ſo that thy father and mother may be glad of thee, and that ſhe that bare thee may reioyce.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 24.</note> Whoſo robbeth his father and mother, and ſayth it is no ſinne: the ſame is like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:11578:53"/> a deſtroyer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 29. 3.</note> Whoſo loueth wiſedom maketh his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a glad man: but he that keepeth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with harlots, ſpendeth away that he hath.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 30. 17.</note> Whoſo laugheth his father to ſcorne, and ſetteth his mothers commaundement at naught, the rauens pick out his eies in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> valley, &amp; deuoured be he of the yong egles.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 3. 3. 4. 5 6. 7.</note> The Lord wil haue the father honoured of the children: and looke what a mother commaundeth her children to doe he will haue it kept. Whoſo honoureth his father, his ſinnes ſhal be forgeuen him, and he that honoureth his mother is like one that ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth treaſure togither. Whoſo honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his father ſhall haue ioy of his owne children, and when he maketh his prayer he ſhall be heard. He that honoureth his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall haue a long life, and he that is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient for the Lords ſake his mother ſhall haue ioy of him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 3. 9.</note> Honour thy father in deede, in word, and in all pacience, that thou mayſt haue Gods bleſſing, and his bleſſing ſhall abide with thee at the laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 3. 10.</note> The bleſſing of the father buildeth vp the houſes of the children: but the mothers
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:11578:54"/> curſe rooteth out the foundations.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 3. 11. 12 13. 14. 15. 16. 17.</note> Reioyce not when thy father is reproued, for it is not honour vnto thee but ſhame. for the worſhippe of a mans father is his owne worſhip, and where the father is without honour, it is the diſhoneſty of the ſonne. My ſonne make much of thy father in his age, &amp; greeue him not as long as he liueth, and if his vnderſtanding faile, haue pacience with him, and deſpiſe him not in thy ſtrength, for the good deede that thou ſheweſt vnto thy father, ſhal not be forgotten, and when thou thy ſelfe wanteſt, it ſhall be rewarded thee, and for thy mothers offence, thou ſhalt be recompenſed with good, yea it ſhal be found for thee in righteouſnes, and in the day of trouble thou ſhalt be remembred: thy ſinnes alſo ſhall melt away, like as the yſe in the faire warme wether. He that forſaketh his father ſhall come to ſhame: and he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth his mother is curſed of God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 27. 28.</note> Honour thy father from thy whole heart: and forget not the ſorowfull trauel that thy mother had with thee: remember that thou waſt borne through them, and howe canſt thou recompence them the things that they haue done for thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Sclaunder.</head>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:11578:54"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 5. 15.</note> BE not a priuy accuſer as long as thou liueſt, and vſe no ſclaunder with thy tongue, for ſhame &amp; ſorow goeth ouer the theefe, &amp; an euill name ouer him that is double tonged: but he that is a priuy accuſer of other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe hated, enuied &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 27. 16.</note> A priuy accuſer of other men ſhall defile his owne ſoule, and be hated of euery man: but he that keepeth his tongue and is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete ſhall come to honour.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 28. 13.</note> The ſclaunderer and double tonged is curſed, for many one that be frendes ſetteth he at variance.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 18. 8.</note> The wordes of a ſclaunderer are very woundes, and goe thorow the innermoſt partes of the body.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Sluggiſhnes and idlenes.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 6. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11. 12.</note> GOe to the Emmet (thou ſluggard) conſider her wayes and learne to be wiſe. She hath no guide nor ouerſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, nor ruler: yet in the ſommer ſhe proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth her meate, and gathereth her foode to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither in the harueſt. Howe long wilt thou ſleepe, thou ſluggiſh man? When wilt thou aryſe out of thy ſleepe? Yea ſleepe on ſtill a litle, ſlumber a litle, foulde thy handes togither yet a litle, that thou mayſt ſleepe: ſo ſhall pouertie come vnto thee
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:11578:55"/> as one that trauaileth by the way, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie like a weaponed man. But if thou be not ſlouthfull, thy harueſt ſhall come as a ſpringing well, and pouertie ſhall flie from thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 10. 4.</note> An ydle hand maketh poore: but a quicke labouring hande maketh riche.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 10. 5.</note> Who ſo gathereth in Summer is wiſe: but he that is ſluggiſh in harneſt, bringeth him ſelfe to confuſion.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 12. 9.</note> A ſimple man which laboureth and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one that is gorgeous and lacketh breade.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 12. 11.</note> He that tilleth his land, ſhall haue plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of breade: but he that followeth ydleneſſe is a very foole.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 12. 24.</note> A diligent hande ſhall beare rule: but the ydle ſhall be vnder tribute.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 13. 4.</note> The ſlogarde would faine haue, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get his deſire: but the ſoule of the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſhall haue plentie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 18. 9.</note> Who ſo is ſlouthfull and ſlacke in his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, is the brother of him that is a waſter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 19. 24.</note> A ſlouthfull man ſhutteth his handes in to his boſome, as in to the potte: and will not take paine to put it to his mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 20. 4.</note> A ſlouthful bodie wil not go to plow for coulde of winter: therefore ſhall he go a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:11578:55"/> begging in Summer, and haue nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 12.</note> The eare to heare, the eye to ſee, the Lord hath made them both: delite not thou in ſleepe, leſt thou come vnto pouertie: but open thine eyes that thou maieſt haue bred ynough.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 26. 14.</note> Like as the doore turneth aboute vpon the henges, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo doth the ſlouthfull welter him ſelfe in his bed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 26. 15.</note> The ſlouthfull bodie thruſteth his hande in to his boſome, and it greueth him to put it againe to his mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 26. 16.</note> The ſlogarde thingeth him ſelfe wiſer then ſeuen men that ſit and teach.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 19.</note> He that tilleth his land ſhal haue plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes of bread: but he that followeth ydle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhall haue pouertie ynough.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 10. 17.</note> Thorow ſlouthfulneſſe the balkes fall downe, and thorow ydle handes it raineth in at the houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 31. 22.</note> In all thy workes be diligent and quick ſo ſhall there no ſickenes happen vnto thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Strife or diſcorde.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 17. 1.</note> BEtter is a dry morſel with quietneſſe, then a houſe full of fatt offering with ſtrife.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 22. 10.</note> Caſt out the ſcornefull man, and ſo ſhall
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:11578:56"/> ſtrife goe out with him: yea variance and ſclaunder ſhall ceaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 26. 20.</note> Where no woode is there the fire goeth out: euen ſo where the tale betrayer is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away, there the ſtrife ceaſeth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 26. 21.</note> Coles kindle heat, &amp; woode the fier: euen ſo doth a brawling fellow ſtirre vp varia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 26. 22.</note> A tale bearers wordes are like men that ſtrike with hammers, but they pearce the inwarde partes of the bodie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 3.</note> It is a mans honour to keepe him ſelfe from ſtrife: but they that haue pleaſure in brauling are fooles euery one.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 8. 1. 2. 3. 4.</note> Striue not with a mighty man leſt thou chaunce to fall into his handes. Make not variance with a riche man, leſt he happen to bring vp an harde quarell againſt thee. Striue not with a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is full of words: and lay no ſtickes vpon his fire. Striue not with him that is angry and cruell, and goe not with him in to wilderneſſe: for bloude is nothing in his ſight, and where there is no helpe he ſhall murther thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Suertiſhippe.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 6. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5.</note> IF thou be ſuertie for thy neighbour and haſte faſtened thine hande for an other man, thou arte bounde with thine owne
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:11578:56"/> wordes, and taken with thine owne ſpeech. Therefore my ſonne doe this &amp; thou ſhalt be diſcharged: when thou art come into thy neighbours daunger, goe thy wayes then ſoone, humble thy ſelf, and with thy friends entreate thy creditour, let not thine eyes ſleepe, nor thine eye liddes ſlumber. Saue thy ſelfe as a Do from the hand of the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, &amp; as a birde from the hand of the fouler.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 15.</note> He that is ſuerty for a ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, hurteth him ſelfe: &amp; he that medleth not with ſuerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is ſure.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17. 18.</note> Whoſo promiſeth by the hand and is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ertie for his neighbour, he is a foole.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 16.</note> Take his garment that is ſuertie for a ſtraunger: and take a pledge of him for the vnknowen mans ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 22. 26.</note> Be not thou one of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bind their hand vpon promiſe, &amp; are ſuerty for weighty cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: for if thou haſt nothing to pay, they ſhal take away thy bedde from vnder thee.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 8. 12.</note> Lend not vnto him that is mightier then thy ſelfe: If thou lendeſt him count it but loſt. Be not fuertie aboue thy power: if thou be, then thinke ſurely to pay it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 29. 15. 16. 17. 18. 19. 20. 21. 22.</note> A good honeſt man is ſuertie for his neighbour, but a wicked perſon letteth him come to ſhame. Forget not the friendſhip of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:11578:57"/> thy ſuertie, for he hath geuen his ſoule for thee. The vngodly deſpiſe the good deed of his ſuertie, and the vnthankefull and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunt leaueth his ſuertie in daunger.</p>
            <p>Some man promiſeth for his neighbour, and when he hath loſt his honeſtie, he ſhall forſake him. Suertiſhip hath deſtroyed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a riche man, &amp; remoued them as the ſea. Mighty people hath it driuen away, &amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to wander in ſtraung cuntries. An vngodly man tranſgreſſing the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of the Lord, ſhal fall into the ſuerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: and though he force him ſelfe to get out, yet ſhall he fall into the iudgement. Helpe thy neighbour out after thy power: and beware that thou thy ſelfe fall not into ſuch debt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Swearing.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> 23. 9. 10 11. 12.</note> LEt not thy mouth be accuſtomed with ſweari<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, for in it there are many falls. Let not the naming of God be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually in thy mouth: and meddle not with the names of Saincts, for thou ſhalt not be excuſed of them: for like as a ſeruant which is oft puniſhed can not be without ſome ſore, euen ſo what ſoeuer he be that ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and nameth God, ſhall not be cleane purged from ſinne. A man that vſeth much
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:11578:57"/> ſwearing ſhall be filled with wickedneſſe, and the plague ſhall neuer goe from his houſe. If he begyle his brother, his fayth ſhal be vpon him: If he knowledge not his ſinne, he maketh a double offence, and if he ſweare in vayne he ſhall not be found righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, for his houſe ſhall be full of plagues. The words of the ſwearer bringeth death.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Tyme.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 3. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8.</note> EVery thing hath a time: yea all that is vnder the heauen hath his conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſeaſon. There is a time to be born and a time to die. There is a time to plant, &amp; a time to plucke vp the thing that is plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. A time to ſlay, a time to make hole. A time to break down, and a time to build vp. A time to weepe, &amp; a time to laugh. A time to mourne, and a time to daunce. A time to caſt away ſtones, &amp; a time to gather ſtones togither. A time to embrace, and a time to refraine from embracing. A time to winne, and a time to loſe. A time to ſpare, &amp; a time to ſpend. A time to cut in peeces, &amp; a time to ſow togither. A time to keepe ſilence, and a time to ſpeake. A time to loue, and a time to hate. A time of warre, and a time of peace.</p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:11578:58"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 7. 10.</note> Say not thou: What is the cauſe that the dayes of the olde tyme were better then they be nowe? for that were no wiſe queſtion.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Truth and lying.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 12. 17.</note> A Iuſt man wil tel the truth, and ſhew the thinge that is right: but a falſe witneſſe deceaueth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 12. 22.</note> The Lord abhorreth lying lippes: but they that labour for truth pleaſe him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 4. 20.</note> My ſonne, make much of the time, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew the thing that is euill, and for thy life ſhame not to ſay the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 4. 25.</note> In no wiſe ſpeake againſt the worde of truth: but be aſhamed of the lyes of thyne owne ignoraunce.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 20. 23. 24. 25.</note> A lye is a wicked ſhame in a man, yet ſhall it be euer in the mouth of the vnwiſe. A theefe is better then a man that is accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed to lye: but they both ſhall haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to heritage. The condicions of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars are vnhoneſt, and their ſhame is euer with them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 12. 13</note> Accept not leaſing againſt thy brother, neither doe the ſame againſt thy friend: Vſe not to make any maner of lye, for the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome thereof is not good.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 40. 12.</note> All brybes and vnrighteouſneſſe ſhall be
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:11578:58"/> put away, but faithfulneſſe and truth ſhall endure for euer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Vanitie of the world.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 1. 2.</note> ALl is but moſt vayne vanitie (ſayth the preacher) and all is moſt vayne (I ſay) and but plaine vanitie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 2. 1. 2 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. 9. 10. 11.</note> Then ſaid I thus in my heart: Now go to, I will take myne eaſe, and haue good dayes. But loe that is vanitie alſo: in ſo much that I ſayde vnto the man geuen to laughter, thou art mad: and to myrth, what doeſt thou? So I thought in my heart to geue my ſelfe vnto wine, and agayne to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply my minde vnto wiſedome, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende fooliſhnes, vntill the tyme (that amonge all the thinges which are vnder the Sunne) I might ſee what were beſt for men to doe, ſo long as they liue vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. I made gorgeous fayre works. I buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me houſes, &amp; pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted vineyardes. I made me orchardes, and gardens of pleaſure, and planted trees in them of all maner fruites. I made pooles of water to water the grene &amp; fruitful trees withal. I bought ſeruaunts and maydens, and had a greate houſholde. As for cattell and ſheepe, I had more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of them then all they that were before
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:11578:59"/> me in Ieruſalem. I gathered ſiluer and golde together, euen a treaſure of kinges and landes. I prouided me ſingers, and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men which coulde plaie on inſtrumentes to make men mirth and paſtime. I gatte me pſalteries and ſonges of muſicke. And I was greater and in more worſhippe, then all my predeceſſours in Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome remained with one: and looke what ſoeuer mine eyes deſired, I let them haue it: and wherin ſoeuer my hearte delited or had any pleaſure, I withhelde it not from it: Thus my hearte reioyſed in all that I did: and this was my portion of all my trauaile. But when I conſidered all the workes that my handes had wrought, and all the labour that I had taken therein: lo all was but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and vexacion of minde, and nothing of any value vnder the Sunne.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 2. 22. 23. 24</note> What getteth a man of all the labour and trauaile of his minde, that he taketh vnder the Sunne, but heauineſſe, ſorowe, and diſquietneſſe all the dayes of his life: in ſo muche that his hearte cannot reſt in the night, this is alſo a vaine thing: is it not better then for a man to eate and drinke and his ſoule to be mery in his labour, yea I ſawe that this alſo was a gift of God.</p>
            <pb n="99" facs="tcp:11578:59"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">VViſ. 13. 1.</note> Vaine are all men which haue not the knowledge of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Wife, good.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 5. 18. 19.</note> BE glad with the wife of thy youth, let her breaſts alway ſatiſfie thee &amp; holde thee euer content with her loue.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 16.</note> A gracious woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mainteineth honeſty, as for the wicked they mainteine riches.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 12. 4.</note> A houſewifely woman is a crowne vnto her huſband, but ſhee that behaueth he ſelfe vnhoneſtly, is a corruption in his bones.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 1.</note> Wiſe women vpholde their houſe: but a fooliſh wife plucketh it downe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 18. 22</note> Who ſo findeth a good wife, findeth a good thing: and receaueth a wholeſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of the Lorde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 18. 22.</note> He that putteth away a good woman, putteth away a good thing: but he that kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth an harlot is a foole and vnwiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 19. 14</note> Houſe and riches may a man haue by the heritage of his elders: but a diſcrete woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is the gifte of the Lorde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 19.</note> Departe not from a diſcrete and good woman that is fallen vnto thee for thy por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the feare of the Lorde: for the gift of her honeſtie is aboue golde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 7. 26.</note> If thou haue a wife after thine owne
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:11578:60"/> minde, forſake her not, but commit not thy ſelfe to the hatefull.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 26. 1. vſque ad 19.</note> Happie is the man that hath a vertuous wife, for the numbre of his yeares ſhall be double. An honeſt woman maketh her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande a ioyfull man, and ſhee ſhall fill the yeares of his life in peace. A verteous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is a noble gifte, which ſhall be geuen for a good porcion vnto ſuch as feare God. Whether a man be riche or poore, he may haue euer a mery hearte, and a cheerefull countenaunce. A louing wife reioyſeth her huſbande, and feedeth his bones with her wiſedome. A woman of fewe wordes is a gifte of God, &amp; to all well murtered mindes may nothing be compared. An honeſt and manerly woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is a gift aboue other giftes, like as the Sunne whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ariſeth is an orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the high heauen of the Lorde, ſo is a verteous wife the bewtie of all her houſe. Like as the clear light is vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delſticke, ſo is the bewtie of the face, vpon an honeſt bodie. Like as the golden pillers are vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſocketh of ſiluer: ſo are the faire legges vpon a woman that hath a conſtant minde. Perpetual are the foundacions that be laide vpon an hole ſtony rocke: ſo are the commaundementes of God, vpon the heart
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:11578:60"/> of an holy woman.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 36. 22. 23. 24.</note> A faire wife reioyceth her huſbande, and a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loueth nothing better: if ſhe be louing and verteous with all, then is not her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande like other men. He that hath gotten a vertuous woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath a goodly poſſeſſion: ſhe is vnto him a helpe, a piller where vpon he reſteth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Wife, euill.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 19. 13.</note> A Brawling wife is like the toppe of an houſe where thorowe it is euer dropping.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 13.</note> It is better to dwell in a corner vnder the houſe toppe, then with a brawling wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in a wide houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 21. 19.</note> It is better to dwell in wilderneſſe, then with a chiding and an angry woman.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 9. 4.</note> Vſe not the companie of a woman, that is a player &amp; a dauncer, and heare her not, leſt thou periſh thorow her entyſing.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 25. 15. vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note> All puniſhment and plage is nothing in compariſon of the plage of the hearte, euen ſo all wickednes, is nothing to the wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a woman. There is not a more wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked heade then the heade of a ſerpent: and there is no wrath aboue the wrath of a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. I will rather dwell with a lyon and a
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:11578:61"/> dragon, then to keepe houſe with a wicked wife. The wickedneſſe of a woman chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth her face, ſhe ſhall muflle her counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce as it were a beare, and as a ſacke ſhal ſhe ſhew it among the neighbours. Her huſband is brought to ſhame among his neighbours, and when he heareth it, it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him to ſigh. All wickedneſſe is but li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to the wickedneſſe of a woman, the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the vngodly ſhall fall vpon her. Like as to clime vp a ſandy way is to the feete of the aged, euen ſo is a wife full of wordes to a ſtill quiet man. If a woman get the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, then is ſhe contrary to her huſband. A wicked wife maketh a ſory heart, an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy countenance, and a dead wound. Weake handes and feeble knees is a woman that her huſband is not the better for. Of the woman came the beginning of ſinne, and thorow her we all are deade. Geue thy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter no paſſage, no not a litle, neither geue a wicked woman her will. If ſhe walke not after thy hand, ſhe ſhall confound thee in the ſight of thine enemies. Cut her of from thy fleſh that ſhe doe not alway abuſe thee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Wyne.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 23. 29.</note> Whoſo hath pleaſure to continue at the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:11578:61"/> wine, leaueth diſhoneſty in his owne dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 20. 1.</note> Wine maketh a man to be ſcornfull, and ſtrong drinke cauſeth a man to be vnquiet: whoſo deliteth therein ſhall neuer be wiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 23. 29. 30.</note> Who hath woe? who hath ſorow? who hath ſtrife? who hath brauling? and who hath woundes without cauſe? or who hath redde eyes? euen they that be euer at the wine and ſeeke exceſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 23. 31.</note> Looke not thou vpon the wine howe red it is, and what a colour it geueth in the glaſſe. It goeth downe ſoftly, but at the laſt it biteth like a ſerpent, and ſtingeth as an adder.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 31. 6.</note> Geue ſtrong drinke vnto ſuch as are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to death, and wine vnto thoſe that mourne: that they may drinke it and forget their miſery and aduerſitie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 31. 27. 28. 29.</note> Wine ſoberly drunken quickeneth the life of man. If thou drinkeſt it meaſurably, thou ſhalt be temperate. What life is it that may continue without wine? What taketh away life? euen death. Wyne was made from the beginning to make him glad, and not for drunkennes. Wine meaſurably dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, is a reioycing of the ſoule &amp; body: but if it be drunken with exceſſe, it maketh bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:11578:62"/> and ſorow vnto the minde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 40. 20.</note> Wine and Muſick reioyce the heart.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Wiſedom, whereof you may read at large 1. 2. 4. 8. 9. of Pro.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 3. 13. 14.</note> WEll is him that findeth wiſedom and obtaineth vnderſtanding: for the getting of it, is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any marchandiſe of ſiluer, and the profite of it is better then golde.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 3. 15. 16. 17. 18. 19. 20.</note> Wiſedom is more worth then precious ſtones, and all the thinges that thou canſt deſire, are not to be compared vnto her. Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her right hand is long life, and vpon her left hand is richeſſe and honour. Her waies are pleaſaunt wayes, and all her pathes are peaceable. She is a tree of life to them that lay holde vppon her, and bleſſed is he that keepeth her faſt. With wiſedome hath the Lorde layd the foundation of the earth, and thorow vnderſtanding hath he ſtabliſhed the heauens. Thorow his wiſedom the dep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes breake vppe, and the cloudes droppe downe the dewe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 4. 7.</note> The chiefe poynt of wiſedome is, that thou be willing to obtayne wiſedom, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all thy goodes to get thee vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:11578:62"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 16. 16.</note> To haue wiſedom in poſſeſſion, is better then to haue golde: &amp; to get vnderſtanding, is rather to be choſen then to haue ſiluer.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">VViſ. 6. 1.</note> Wiſedom is better then ſtrength, and a man of vnderſtanding is more worth then one that is ſtrong.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">VViſ. 7. 28. 29.</note> God loueth no man but him in whom wiſedom dwelleth, for ſhe is more bewtiful then the Sunne, and geueth more light then the ſtarres, &amp; the day is not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vnto her, for vpon the day commeth night, but wickedneſſe can not ouercome wiſedom, and fooliſhneſſe may not be with her.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 1. 1.</note> All wiſedom cometh of God the Lorde, and hath bene euer with him and is before all time.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Wrath or anger</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 12. 16.</note> A Foole vttereth his wrath in all the haſt: but a diſcret ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> couereth wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 27. 3.</note> The ſtone is heauy, and the ſande weighty: but a fooles wrath is heauier then them both.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 27. 4.</note> Wrath is a cruell thing, &amp; furiouſnes is a very te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt: but who is able to abide enuy.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 28. 1.</note> He that ſeeketh vengeaunce ſhall finde vengeaunce of the Lorde, which ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly keepe him his ſinnes.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:11578:63"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus 28. 10.</note> An angry man kindleth variaunce, and the vngodly diſquiet friendes, and putteth diſcord among them that be at peace. The more wood there is, the more vehement is the fire: and the mightier that men be, the greater is the wrath, and the longer the ſtrife endureth, the more it burneth. An ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty brauling kindleth a fire, and haſty ſtrife ſheddeth bloud.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="subject">
            <head>Witneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 12. 17.</note> A Iuſt man wil tel the truth, and ſhew the thing that is right: but a falſe witneſſe deceiueth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou 14. 5.</note> A faithfull witneſſe will not diſſemble: but a falſe record will make a lye.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 14. 25.</note> A faithfull witneſſe deliuereth ſoules: but a deceitful witneſſe bringeth forth lies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 19. 5.</note> A falſe witneſſe ſhall not remaine vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed: and he that ſpeaketh lyes ſhall not eſcape.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 21. 28.</note> A falſe witneſſe ſhall periſh: but he that is a true man boldly ſpeaketh that he hath hearde. Be no falſe witneſſe againſt thy neighbour, and ſpeake no falſhood with thy lippes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb facs="tcp:11578:63"/>
            <head>THE CONCLVSION of the Booke.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His much (gentle reader) had I gathered for myne ovvne inſtruction, not eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſaying that is of impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, for there is none at all in any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the holy Scripture vnfruitefull or vnneceſſary: but thoſe, vvhich in my ſimple iudgement, ſeemed moſt vvaigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and pythy, and vſuall. And vvhereas contrary matters be knit togither in one ſentence, as pride and lovvlines, health and ſicknes, proſperitie and aduerſitie, &amp; ſuch others, (vvhich oftentimes falleth out as by reading euery man may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue) I haue likevviſe placed them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, that the one by the other might the better be perceiued. For ſuch is the nature of contraries, (as Ariſtotle vvit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth) that, <hi>Inuicem oppoſita magis eluceſcunt.</hi> And this my labour I truſt euery vvell diſpoſed perſon vvill take in
<pb facs="tcp:11578:64"/> good part: ſeing that I haue ſet it forth for none other intent, then as vvell as I might to make others partakers of my commoditie. And to let the ignoraunt plainly vnderſtand, that the Scripture it ſelfe being diligently vveyed, may geue knovvledge ſufficient, euen in vvorldly affayres. And I vvould to God, that all our dealinges vvere meaſured by this rule, then should not Chriſtians be found ſo vnfaithfull, yea faithleſſe in dealing vvith their brethren. VVhich fault novv a dayes, euen in this our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey of England is to to notorious. Yea <hi>Fides,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Tullies definition, that is, <hi>Dictorum factorum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conſtantia &amp; veritas,</hi> is <hi>Rara auis</hi> in (England) <hi>nigro<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lima cigno.</hi> Yea truely in this fault, vve be much vvorſe then our forefathers, vvho though they liued in a time of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, &amp; knevv not the vvill of God openly by his vvord, yet shevved in dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling one vvith an other, better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and obedience then vve doe.
<pb facs="tcp:11578:64"/> But God of his mercy vvho novv telleth vs our dueties, euery vvay, and euery vvhere in plaine english, vvill (I truſt) lighten our heartes, and geue vs grace to shevv forth the ſame in vvorks, vvhich vve profeſſe in vvordes, or els no doubt our condemnation shall be the greater, nay our forefathers shall riſe to condemn vs. God graunt vs all of his heauenly vviſedom. And as thorovv vviſedom,<note place="margin">Prou. 8. 15. 16. 17.</note> Kings doe raigne, and Princes make iuſt lavves, and Lords beare rule, and iudges of the earth execute iudgement: So (God graunt) that our Soueraign Lady Queene Elizabeth, thorovv vviſedom may long raigne and make good lavves. That her Lordes &amp; Counſayle thorovv vviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom may beare rule, and all Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of England thorovv vviſedom may exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute true iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:11578:65"/>
            <head>A TABLE OF THE COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MON PLACES.</head>
            <list>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>Aduerſitie and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. pag. 1.</item>
               <item>Aduoutrie and Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. pag. 2.</item>
               <item>Age. pag. 4.</item>
               <item>Almes. pag. 5.</item>
               <item>Ambition. pag. 7.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>Battaile. Ibidem</item>
               <item>Bewtie. pag. 8.</item>
               <item>Boaſting &amp; Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. pag. 9.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>Citie. Ibidem.</item>
               <item>Company. pag. 10.</item>
               <item>Communication or talke. pag. 11.</item>
               <item>Conſtancie. pag. 13.</item>
               <item>Correction. Ibidem</item>
               <item>Countenaunce. pag. 15</item>
               <item>Counſayle and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaylers. Ibidem</item>
               <item>Couetouſnes. Looke more in Liberalitie. pag. 18.</item>
               <item>Curioſitie. pag. 19.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>Daughter. Ibidem</item>
               <item>Death. pag. 21.</item>
               <item>Delicate liuing. pa. 23.</item>
               <item>Diet. Ibidem</item>
               <item>Diſſembling. pag. 24.</item>
               <item>Doings of men. Looke Good men. pag. 25.</item>
               <item>Dreames. pag. 27.</item>
               <item>Drunkenneſſe. Looke more in wine. pag. 28.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>Enemie. Looke more in Loue and euill will. Ibidem</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:11578:65"/>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>Father and mother. pag. 29.</item>
               <item>Feare of the Lorde. pag. 31.</item>
               <item>Folly. pag. 33.</item>
               <item>Fortune, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in deed nothing elſe but the proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God. pa. 35</item>
               <item>Friendship. pag. 37.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>Giftes or revvardes. pag. 39.</item>
               <item>God. pag. 40.</item>
               <item>Good men and euill. pag. 43.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H.</head>
               <item>Health and Sickneſſe. pag. 45.</item>
               <item>Houſe and Huſbandry pag. 46.</item>
               <item>Houſevvife. pag. 47.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>Iudge and Iudgement. pag. 48.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K</head>
               <item>Knowledge and Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. pag. 52.</item>
               <item>King or Prince. pag. 53</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>Labour. Looke more in Slouthfulneſſe. pag. 56.</item>
               <item>Lavve of God &amp; man. pag. 57.</item>
               <item>Lending and borovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. pag. 58.</item>
               <item>Liberalitie. pag. 60.</item>
               <item>Loue and euill vvill. Ibidem</item>
               <item>Liuing. pag. 62.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>Maners. pag. 64.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:11578:66"/>
               <item>Marchaunt. pag. 66.</item>
               <item>Meaſure and vvayght. Ibidem</item>
               <item>Mercy. Ibidem</item>
               <item>Myrth and ioy. pag. 68.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>Name or fame. pa. 69.</item>
               <item>Neighbour. pag. 70.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>Obedience and rule. pag. 71.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>Pacience. pag. 72.</item>
               <item>Pouertie. pag. 73.</item>
               <item>Prayſe. pag. 74.</item>
               <item>Prayer. pag. 75.</item>
               <item>Prieſtes. Ibidem.</item>
               <item>Phiſician and Phiſick. pag. 76.</item>
               <item>Pride and Lowlineſſe. pag. 77.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>Richeſſe. pag. 79.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>Seruaunt. pag. 82.</item>
               <item>Shame, vvhereof vve ought to be asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and vvhere of not. pag. 84.</item>
               <item>Sonne, and the duety of children towards the parents. pag. 85.</item>
               <item>Sclaunder. pag. 89.</item>
               <item>Sluggishneſſe &amp; Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Ibidem.</item>
               <item>Strife or diſcord. pa. 91</item>
               <item>Suertiship. pag. 92.</item>
               <item>Swearing. pag. 94.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>Time. pag. 95.</item>
               <item>Truth and lying. pa. 96</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V</head>
               <item>Vanity of the vvorlde. pag. 97.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>VV</head>
               <item>VVife good. pag. 99.</item>
               <item>VVife euill. pag. 101.</item>
               <item>VVine. pag. 102.</item>
               <item>VViſedom. pag. 104.</item>
               <item>VVrath or anger. pag. 105.</item>
               <item>VVitneſſe. pag. 106.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:11578:66"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Thomas Vautrollier, featuring a woman's head with cornucopias (McKerrow 179)</figDesc>
                  <p>T. V.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
